<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Psalterium Carolinum. The devotions of His sacred Majestie in his solitudes and sufferings, rendred in verse. / Set to musick for 3 voices and an organ, or theorbo, by John Wilson Dr. and music professor of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Wilson, John, 1595-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5243A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1076_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208646</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867574</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1076[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Psalterium Carolinum. The devotions of His sacred Majestie in his solitudes and sufferings, rendred in verse. / Set to musick for 3 voices and an organ, or theorbo, by John Wilson Dr. and music professor of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, John, 1595-1674.</author>
                  <author>Stanley, Thomas, 1625-1678.</author>
                  <author>Lawes, Henry, 1602-1645.</author>
                  <author>Gauden, John, 1605-1662.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5 v. ([280] p.) : music  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Martin and James Allestrey, and are to be sold at the Bell in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Vol. 1 contains twenty-seven short odes by Thomas Stanley, based on chapters 1-26 and 28 of the "Eikon basilike", the authorship of which was originally attributed to Charles I, but according to Madan (pp. 125-33) was written by John Gauden, who probably included some authentic writings of the king. ; vols. 2-5 contain Stanley's odes set to music by John Wilson.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N² ; pi²  a1 A-O² ; pi²  a1 L-2A² ; pi²  a1 X-2L² ; pi²  a1 B-K² .</note>
                  <note>Leaf "a" in vols. 2-5 contains a dedication to John Wilson, signed: Henry Lawes.</note>
                  <note>The title pages to vols. 2-5 are in the same setting as the title of vol. 1, but for the Scriptural quotation is substituted: Set to musick for 3 voices and an organ, or theorbo, by John Wilson Dr. and musick professor of Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Variant: with an unsigned leaf in vol. 2 containing an address by Wilson signed: I.W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Musical settings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Songs, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:1"/>
                  <p>Pſalterium Carolinum.</p>
                  <p>THE DEVOTIONS OF HIS SACRED MAJESTIE IN HIS SOLITUDES AND SUFFERINGS, Rendred in Verſe.</p>
                  <p>Set to Muſick for 3 Voices and an Organ, or Theorbo, By <hi>John Wilſon</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. and Muſick Profeſſor of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device? (not in McKerrow): angel standing with one foot on a bell, blowing a trumpet</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <unclear>VIIVENERANDAISONES</unclear>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martin</hi> and <hi>James Alleſtrey,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bell in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:2"/>
                  <p>TO THE GLORY OF GOD, THE SACRED MEMORY OF HIS LATE MAIESTIE, AND TO THE RIGHT REVEREND CLERGY OF THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND, <hi>JOHN WILSON,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. in Muſick, dedicates this his laſt of labours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:3"/>
                  <head>Faults eſcaped in printing, which the curteous Reader is deſired to amend with his penn.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In Cantus primus,</head>
                  <p>SOng 2 line 1 the firſt quaver muſt ſtand after the ſecond. S. 2 l. 3 after the Crochet in Ela muſt be a prick. S. 3. l. 4 after the firſt Crochet muſt be another in Ela. S. 8 l. 7 the laſt Crochet in Befabemie muſt be ſharp. S.ibid. l. 11 the minnum in Alamire muſt be in Cſolfa. S. 9. l. 3 the prick between the two Minnums muſt be out. S. 17 l. 7 the Crochet in Cſolfa at the latter end muſt be in Alamire. S. 22. l. 11. next to the prick minnum before the Quaver in Cſolfa muſt be the next in Befabemie. S. 26 l. 15 the fiſt note muſt be a Crochet, and the prick muſt be out.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:3"/>
                  <head>To his friend (and formerly, fellow-ſervant to his late Majeſtie) <hi>JOHN WILSON</hi> Dr. in Muſick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I do love thee, friend, I now would ſhew it,</l>
                     <l>And do't in Rhime too, though I am no Poet;</l>
                     <l>Yet all that I could ſay, would but appear</l>
                     <l>Fruitleſs, and inſignificantly here,</l>
                     <l>Since nothing, truly, can thy worth explain,</l>
                     <l>But the compoſures of thine own rich brain.</l>
                     <l>Thou need'ſt no Trumpet to proclaim thy Fame,</l>
                     <l>Thy Lyre moſt ſweetly warbles forth thy name;</l>
                     <l>Which every one muſt needs admire that hears,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he have nor Soul, nor Senſe, nor Ears.</l>
                     <l>This tribute all muſt pay, but none can raiſe</l>
                     <l>(Unleſs he have an equall skill) thy praiſe.</l>
                     <l>From long acquaintance and experience, I</l>
                     <l>Could tell the World thy known integrity;</l>
                     <l>Unto thy Friend thy true and honeſt heart,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n mind, good nature, all, but thy great Art,</l>
                     <l>Which I but dully underſtand; who do</l>
                     <l>To ſhadow't out, muſt have expreſsions too,</l>
                     <l>(If with thy merits they proportion keep)</l>
                     <l>As high, and apt, as is thy judgement deep.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus Diamonds Diamonds cut, Kings judge of Kings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Art cann't be prais'd enough by artleſs thigns.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:4"/>
                     <l>Excuſe me then, if I have no deſigns</l>
                     <l>Impoſsible, and needleſs by theſe lines,</l>
                     <l>So low, to raiſe thy high perfection,</l>
                     <l>And light my Candle at thy noon-day Sun:</l>
                     <l>I could ſay much were I with Raptures fir'd,</l>
                     <l>Were I, as I muſt think thou art, inſpir'd;</l>
                     <l>For this I know, and muſt ſay't to thy praiſe,</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt gone, in Muſick, unknown wayes,</l>
                     <l>Haſt cut a path where there was none before,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Magellan</hi> traced an unknown ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Thou taught'ſt our Language, firſt, to ſpeak in Tone,</l>
                     <l>Gav'ſt the right accents and proportion;</l>
                     <l>And above all (to ſhew thy excellence)</l>
                     <l>Thou underſtand'ſt good words, and do'ſt ſet ſenſe;</l>
                     <l>Hadſt none to imitate, and few will be</l>
                     <l>Able t' expreſs inimitably thee.</l>
                     <l>Go on then, <hi>Phoebus</hi> like, thine own courſe runne,</l>
                     <l>Fearleſs of being out-ſhin'd by a Mock-Sun.</l>
                     <l>Doggs at the Moon may barke, but never dare</l>
                     <l>Againſt the glorious Sun ſo much as ſtare:</l>
                     <l>Go on ſecure, that <hi>Wilſons</hi> honoured name</l>
                     <l>Shall have, as it deſerves, immortall Fame.</l>
                     <l>Call, O call back thy reſolution</l>
                     <l>Of not compoſing more; Springs allwaies run,</l>
                     <l>The World would ſuffer elſe, and thy great name</l>
                     <l>Be leſſen'd; then do not bound thy boundleſs fame;</l>
                     <l>But, like the Sun, ſtill ſcatter beams of light,</l>
                     <l>Nor the whole World, and thine own worth benight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſure if men do ſingle Ingots prize,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll hugg the Mine where all perfection lies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HENRY LAWES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div n="cantus primus" type="partbook">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:4"/>
                  <head>Pſalterium Carolinum. CANTVS PRIMVS.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="ode">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord haſt made us ſee that pious thoughts Of future reformation for paſt faults, Nor ſatisfie thy juſtice or prevent, Alwaies the ſtroaks of thy dire puniſhment: Our hopes ore laid by ſin
<pb facs="tcp:119890:5"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> on thee depend For pardon, not on our reſolves t'amend. When by vindictive judgments on us laid. Thou haſt thy glory in our ſhame diſplaid. And how unſafe it is ſhown us by theſe; To dare t'offend on after hopes to pleaſe: Thy mercies then I truſt the bleſsings may Reſtore, which wrong'd we forc't thee ſnatch away.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:5"/>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou whoſe mercies know no bound, Pardon my com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plyant Sin. Death in me the guiltleſs found, Who his Refuge ſhould have been. To her ſelf and thee my ſoul, Her tranſgreſsion o╌pen layes, Cleanſe we from a guilt ſo foule. And thy mercies I ſhall praiſe. With the crime my heart withſtood, Did my differing hand comply: Yet
<pb facs="tcp:119890:6"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> if Bath'd in thy rich blood, Snow my whiteneſs ſhall outvye. Juſtice let me learn of thine, Who for death unjuſtly given, Future dangers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, In╌to greater now am driven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ode">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou in heaven, and in my heart, My witneſs art, If to oppreſs the innocent I ever meant; Then
<pb facs="tcp:119890:6"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> let my foe my life confound, And tread my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to the ground. The miſts, which coſen humane ſight, Shrinke from thy light. The heart and reins thy ſearching eyes Anatomize. Truth wrapt in darkneſs, loſt in doubt, To day reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, O ſhine out.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:7"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:7"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:8"/>
                     <head>IIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee I fly thou ſole defence of my inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded innocence, Who onely canſt the ſtubborn Main, And people more inrag'd reſtrain. The flouds, the flouds o'reſwell their bounds; Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers my threatned ſoul ſurrounds; Mine and my Realms in╌i╌qui╌ty, The tumults, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults
<pb facs="tcp:119890:8"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of our ſoules gainſt thee; Theſe popular Inundations cauſe, That bear down loy╌al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Lawes. But thou to Seas did'ſt fix a ſhore, And from the deluge earth reſtore; O quel theſe ſal╌vage beaſts, and me From their tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rapines free.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:9"/>
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my God I ſtill appeal, Whoſe all diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eyes re╌veale The clouds that humane thoughts conceale. A heart thou gav'ſt me to beſtow Much on my Subjects, which muſt now Learn much from them to undergo. Thy will be done, and ours deni'd, When moſt to thine
<pb facs="tcp:119890:9"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it ſeems ally'd, And theirs who thee pretend their guide: Inſtruct me wiſely to imploy Thy croſſes that my hopes deſtroy, As the ful╌fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of my joy I raiſed my own fears theirs ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, Unſetled mine to fix their ſtate, Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence my love with hate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:10"/>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Native freedome Lord preſerve, Which bids our wills thy Will obey. Yet from our Conſcience never ſwerve, Whilſt mens decrees with Law we weigh, And Reaſon, nor of ought allow, But that to which our judgments bow. Where fixt by thee I did reſide, That Place by
<pb facs="tcp:119890:10"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Subjects forc'd I quitted, Yet for their good my ſelf deny'd, In all to my diſpoſe ſubmitted. Let no demands in Tumults preſt, From my conſent unjuſt power wreſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="ode">
                     <head>VII</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thoſe whom thou in vowes haſt tied. Yet now by diſtance doſt divide. Here or in Heaven u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:11"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Defend us from de╌ſpite╌full foes. And by the ſufferings they impoſe, Prepare us for thy ſight. Though in Religion we diſſent, Hear our Devotions joyntly bent. Thy ſacred Truth to finde Love in our equal hearts infuſe, Of thee and him who us t'excuſe His ſinleſs life reſign'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:11"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho vengeance on my wrongs haſt ſhowne, And by my foes, my foes or'ethrown. Let not his fall invite My ſoul by cloſe delight, To make thy juſt revenge her own: Thou haſt reverted on his head The miſchief he for others ſpread, Un╌wiſh'd unask'd by me, That all the earth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:12"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> might ſee, Thou didſt my cauſe in judgment plead. I will not, dare not imprecate The like on all that bear me hate. No to their ſouls diſpence pardon and penitence. Charg'd with no due affli╌cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons weight, dprive me Not of Theams ſo fit for mercy; But their ſins remit whoſe bold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit climbes, Next thoſe ungratefull crimes, Of which thou me art pleas'd t'acquit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:12"/>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough humane clouds thy Rayes Like lightning glide, No prejudice thy ſentence ſwayes, For knowledge is thy judgments guide. The proud my ſoul oppoſe And ſlight thy Lawes, Help Lord, for many are my foes: They hate me yet without a cauſe, I never did (thou
<pb facs="tcp:119890:13"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knoweſt) theſe broyles begin. In which though I adventure moſt, yet I am certain leaſt to win. But oft deplor'd and ſtrove with care t'avoyd, My life ſuch dangers could not love. Better to ſave then kill employ'd, My other ſuff'rings far their Calumnie Outweighs, who tell the world this war (my greateſt croſſe) was raiſ'd by me. Yet this by ſilence I to men would owne. Might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:13"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it their malice ſatis╌fie, whilſt thou my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence haſt knowne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="ode">
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my God to thee I fly, ſtronger than the enemy, Heaven nor Earth are wiſht by me In compariſon of thee Let me be when all deny'd. More than all by thee ſupply'd. Haſte to help
<pb facs="tcp:119890:14"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thou fail'ſt not thoſe who their truſt in thee repoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="ode">
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternal wiſdom arm'd with might, With truth and right my Reaſon clear; To which to make my will adhere, No threats may from their dictates fright. Thou didſt not raiſe me to a Throne, To
<pb facs="tcp:119890:14"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> barr me common li╌ber╌ty. Shall that be nam'd a crime in me, Which others as a vertue own? Unjuſtly they their King deny The free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which all mortals claim: Whilſt even them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves exact the ſame, With partial perti╌naci╌ty. To thee I pray who through the Maze Of my own thoughts, and ſuits (like ſnares ſpred to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve my ſoul in cares) Canſt ſurely guide:
<pb facs="tcp:119890:15"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> make plain thy waies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="ode">
                     <head>XII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy mercies Lord, (hence in diſpleaſure fled) On me and my torn Kingdoms I implore; Whoſe loſſe we both too juſtly merited, But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can deſerve thou ſhouldſt reſtore. Thou ſeeſt the cruelty that Chriſtians uſe, In the falſe colours
<pb facs="tcp:119890:15"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Religion dy'd. As if the names of Chriſtians they ſhould loſe, Unleſs they one another cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd. Since we thy Truth and Charity deſpis'd, Error and Hatred now their room poſſeſs, My God, O pardon thoſe thou haſt chaſtis'd. Our wounds with penitential balme redreſſe: Make not our ſufferings leſs in thy eſteeme, and to our Conſcience let our ſinns appear, As they i'th'
<pb facs="tcp:119890:16"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> mirror of thy judgements ſeem, Which to ſmall crimes are never ſo ſevere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="ode">
                     <head>XIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y troubles, Lord, are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti╌ply'd, O ſuccour the diſtreſt: in ſimpleſt truth thy Servant guide, The wiſeſt Intereſt. From the aſſociate ſtrength of thoſe Be thou my juſt defence, Who for the
<pb facs="tcp:119890:16"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Serpents craft depoſe The Doves white innocence. Though to oppreſs me they agree, Combin'd in mutuall aid: Let not my Soul and Honour be To their deceits betray'd. Devotion and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance thou Canſt in their hearts renew, That him they may reſtore whom now They eager ea╌ger╌ly purſue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:17"/>
                     <head>XIIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord I to thee direct my cries, My ſubjects forward Oaths remit. Quicken their ſence of thoſe firm ties, By Law upon their Conſcience knit, With which no pious, no pretence Of Refor╌ma╌tion can diſpence: Religion owns no injurie, No Sacriledge by thee allow'd, Though mask'd
<pb facs="tcp:119890:17"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> with Hate t'Idolitry. Their zeale diſguiſed fraud uncloud: Things holy 'tis a ſnare to take, And after Vowes enquirie make.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="ode">
                     <head>XV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord thou ſeeſt my wrongs abound. Lions enrag'd my Soul ſurround, With poiſnous words, Their tongues like ſwords, Their teeth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:18"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> like Arrows wound. My foes reproach me all the day, And ſworn deceits together lay; My God, how long Shall they grow ſtrong, Who with vain Lies inveigh? The calumnies which they have ſown One every ſide, to thee are known, Hold not thy peace, Leaſt they increaſe, And bury my Renown. The lyar thou wilt ruinate, The bloody and the falſe do'ſt hate;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:18"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Let my upright Intents, a light Clear as the Sun dilate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="ode">
                     <head>XVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU ſtill the ſame for ever bleſt, Whom mercies infinite inveſt, In various conſtancy expreſt. Thou haſt us with new ſenſe indu'd, Of our old wants; nor ſcorn'ſt renu'd Deſires,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:19"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> in unchang'd words purſu'd. Still let our fix'd Devotions join; Our ſuits to thy firm will encline; Our fervent ſpirits move by thine. For thou, in all perfection wiſe, Nor novelty in prayer doſt prize, Nor pious conſtancy deſpiſe. By thy command prefering neither, Left in thy Churches power together, To uſe but not diſparage either.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:19"/>
                     <head>XVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is known, Who haſt appointed me to own Thy ſacred faith's defence. O let me not, of thee forlorn, Againſt my Conſcience be ore╌born, By Floods of violence. Up Lord in thine own cauſe ariſe, Leaſt Schiſme make thy Church its prize, And
<pb facs="tcp:119890:20"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> trample on her power, From thee continued to our time, When Wealth is made her fatall crime; Her ſinn is her fair dower. Whom ſome have plunderd, others wound, The reſt deſerted as they found, Or in her ſufferrings joy. May I her hurts and wants relieve, The power which I from thee receive, Teach me for thee t'imploy. To her that love be ſtill ſuſtain'd I owe as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:20"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſtian, though reſtrain'd As King, from all my right. The bounties on thy Church diſplaid, By Providence let none invade, With ſacrilegious might.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="ode">
                     <head>XVIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Peace and Reaſon Lord, Delighting in accord, The wicked, who from Sinn, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:21"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> offer'd grace would win! Whoſe mercy courts to ſave, Though power to kill thou have, (Our hearts to ſoftneſs woo'd, In our Redeemers blood) Perſwade us to agree Both with our ſelves and thee, As men and Chriſtians ought. Peace often have I ſought, But it no ſooner name Than Wars my foes proclaime. Our actions never may Deſtructive pasſions ſway. Our
<pb facs="tcp:119890:21"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> judgements clear, that we Thy truth may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee. Our ſtubborn hearts incline, In bonds of Peace to joyn. Our irreligious hate To thee, O disſipate: That to our ſelves remove With interchanged love, The war our ſins have wrought, With peace which Chriſt hath bought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:22"/>
                     <head>XIX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith ready joy O let me, Lord, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree To be orecome when thou wilt have it ſo: Inſtruct me in the nobleſt victory, By patience to ſubdue my ſelf and Foe; Conqueſts, like Chriſt's, a Chriſtian King beſt ſhew. Mould us to piety betwixt thy hands; Preſt by thy
<pb facs="tcp:119890:22"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> left, ſupported by thy right. Pardon the pride of our ſucceſsfull Bands, And the repinings of our luckleſs fight; When (truſting in our own) denied thy Might. When we are ought or nothing, be thou all; That thy wide glories the whole world may fill, Or in our conqueſt or inglorious fall. Thou know'ſt with what regret I ſuffer ill, From thoſe whoſe good's the ſcope
<pb facs="tcp:119890:23"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of all my will. The ills they force me to inflict, I bear; And in their puniſhments, my own embrace. Victor or vanquiſh'd, ſince a double ſhare Of certain ſuffering doth my hope diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, Grant me a double portion of thy grace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="ode">
                     <head>XX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou who beauty canſt return To them
<pb facs="tcp:119890:23"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> that mourn; And the diſguis'd pretext of Art, To truth convert; O let us not by ſhews beguil'd, Seem pure without, within defil'd. Within, where moſt deform'd we are, Be our firſt care: Then with clear eyes, the Church, we may, And State ſurvey. Our hearts, our ſpirits, Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, That we thy dictates may purſue.
<pb facs="tcp:119890:24"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Upon our foul diſorders, bred By them who (led With rage) to purge us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, With pitty looke. Quench thou the fire that Factions raiſe, From Reformations ſpecious blaze. As their diviſion, Lord, proclaims Their weak bad aims; So let us (in thoſe fires refin'd) In love be join'd; From pasſions freed: bleſt with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:24"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> increaſe Of inward vertue outward peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="ode">
                     <head>XXI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord who by thy wiſe Decree, Doſt our contingency diſpoſe; Make me thy conſtant mercies ſee, In the advantage of my foes. Thou canſt their Counſells turn away, And their devices ruinate: Who all my ſecrets
<pb facs="tcp:119890:25"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> open lay, To worke me in my peoples hate. To thy Omniſcience I repair, Witneſſe with my integrity, How falſe the wreſted Comments are, Which they to what I write apply. The ill, directed by their aim To me, ſo turn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their head, That they may be involv'd in ſhame, And with confuſion overſpread.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:25"/>
                     <head>XXII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou who all ſouls, all con ſcien╌ces doſt ſway, To thee I look diſmaid; To thy protection I commit my way, Thou who my life didſt aid, Still in my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe canſt thy ſtrength diſplay. A fierie Pillar in darke nights to me, And with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:26"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy light direct, In ſcorching daies a cloudy Pillar be; And with thy ſhade protect. O let me find both ſun and ſhield in thee. My life I was not by perverſneſſe wrought To hazards thus t'expoſe, But Reaſon, Honour, and Religion taught To guard my ſelf from thoſe, Whoſe impious force to wreſt them from me ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:26"/>
                     <head>XXIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that alone art infinite In good, and greatneſſe; dwel'ſt with me. Weigh'd with thy preſence, life is light, Thy ſervice perfect liberty: Own me for thine, I cannot but be free. As I am man, with reaſon bleſſe, With Zeal as Chriſtian, Right as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:27"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> King. Of outwards ſtript, let me poſſeſſe Thee in the joyes that from thee ſpring; Which gainſt my will no force can from me wring. Let not my pasſion over╌boyle, To fruitleſs rage, or ſordid fear; They think him helpleſs whom they foyle: But let thy chearfull light appear, And ſecure freedom ſhall my glories cleer. Befitting my afflicted
<pb facs="tcp:119890:27"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtate, A patient conſtancy beſtow. My ſtrength and hopes are disſipate, My ſelf impriſon'd by the foe: O be not far, leſt they too mighty grow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="ode">
                     <head>XXIV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayers I ſend, The help that others my diſtreſs deny, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:28"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy asſiſtant ſpirit Lord ſupply. To dulneſs life, light to my darkneſs lend. Thou Sun, that beams of righteouſneſs doſt ſpread, Thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſpring of heavenly light and heat, Both warmth and clearneſs in my heart beget, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, and for thy ſervant intercede. Fullneſs, ſufficience, favour, thee array; Enough thou comfort art, and company. Thou art my King,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:28"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> my Prieſt and Prophet be; Rule, teach, pray, in me, for me, with me ſtay. Jacob, who ſingly did with thee conteſt In ſacred duell, thee his Second had: He conquer'd, and a blesſing (by thy ayd) From thee, with wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come violence did wreſt. With mercy on thy ſervant be intent, Who his devotions once with them did joyn, Whoſe fervour might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:29"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> inflame the cold of mine; When to thy Houſe with joy and peace we went.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="ode">
                     <head>XXV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, my King, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eare; My cry, to thee directed, hear. Incens'd, I ſaid, we from thy care Are caſt. Yet thou receiv'ſt my prayer. Thy rigour who can ſatisfy?
<pb facs="tcp:119890:29"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> But to thy mercies Sinners fly. Lord I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my offence, Dilated in my emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. The ſinns I act, or do permit By unimproved power, acquit. Rebellious I to thee became, Now, priſoner to my Subjects am. Yet though reſtrain'd my perſon be, By Grace enlarge my heart to thee; Though <hi>David</hi>'s piety I want, His griefs I have;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:30"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> his comforts grant</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord, thou ſacred unity, In an undivided Trine, Thoſe combin'd in mercy ſee; Whom thy juſtice doth disjoin. Save me from diſſenting foes, Who my prayers and pity need; And each other now oppoſe, Though to fight with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:30"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> me agreed. All diſcording parties guide To the peace from which they ſtray, Whilſt they ſerve or court a ſide, Not the voice of Law obey. Make me willingly to go Where thy providence will lead: And the change of things be╌low, In thy conſtant preſence read. Make me by thy skillfull hand, Such as thou wouldſt have me be; Then waft me ſafely
<pb facs="tcp:119890:31"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:31"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:32"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to that land, Where peace e╌ver dwells with thee. Spare our Cities (Lord) impure Through their wealth and plenty made; In their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſecure, By ſecurity betrai'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that fill'ſt Heaven and earth, O King of Kings, In whom no death, whence life
<pb facs="tcp:119890:32"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> eternal ſprings. Who canſt our ſouls unto the yawning Grave, Juſtly condemn or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully ſave. Better be dead t'our ſelves, in thee ſurvive; Than rob'd of thee, and to our ſelves alive. O let the bitter means that agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate My fall, thy comforts in my ſoul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. If thou art with me, fear ſhall not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail Though I ſhould walk along death's ſhady
<pb facs="tcp:119890:33"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> vale. Weak mortall man may with his fate contend, But 'tis thy grace muſt ſtrength to vanquiſh lend. Thou know'ſt, as man, what 'tis to dye, with me, Teach me by Death to live, my God, with thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:33"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:34"/>
                  <p>Pſalterium Carolinum. THE DEVOTIONS OF HIS SACRED MAJESTIE IN HIS SOLITUDES AND SUFFERINGS, Rendred in Verſe.</p>
                  <p>Set to Muſick for 3 Voices and an Organ, or Theorbo, By <hi>John Wilſon</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. and Muſick Profeſſor of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device? (not in McKerrow): angel standing with one foot on a bell, blowing a trumpet</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <unclear>VI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>VENERANDA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>SONES</unclear>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martin</hi> and <hi>James Alleſtrey,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bell in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:35"/>
                  <head>To his friend (and formerly, fellow-ſervant to his late Majeſtie) <hi>JOHN WILSON</hi> Dr. in Muſick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I do love thee, friend, I now would ſhew it,</l>
                     <l>And do't in Rhime too, though I am no Poet;</l>
                     <l>Yet all that I could ſay, would but appear</l>
                     <l>Fruitleſs, and inſignificantly here,</l>
                     <l>Since nothing, truly, can thy worth explain,</l>
                     <l>But the compoſures of thine own rich brain.</l>
                     <l>Thou need'ſt no Trumpet to proclaim thy Fame,</l>
                     <l>Thy Lyre moſt ſweetly warbles forth thy name;</l>
                     <l>Which every one muſt needs admire that hears,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he have nor Soul, nor Senſe, nor Ears.</l>
                     <l>This tribute all muſt pay, but none can raiſe</l>
                     <l>(Unleſs he have an equall skill) thy praiſe.</l>
                     <l>From long acquaintance and experience, I</l>
                     <l>Could tell the World thy known integrity;</l>
                     <l>Unto thy Friend thy true and honeſt heart,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n mind, good nature, all, but thy great Art;</l>
                     <l>Which I but dully underſtand; who do</l>
                     <l>To ſhadow't out, muſt have expreſsions too,</l>
                     <l>(If with thy merits they proportion keep)</l>
                     <l>As high, and apt, as is thy judgement deep.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus Diamonds Diamonds cut, Kings judge of Kings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Art cann't be prais'd enough by artleſs thigns.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:36"/>
                     <l>Excuſe me then, if I have no deſigns</l>
                     <l>Impoſsible, and needleſs by theſe lines,</l>
                     <l>So low, to raiſe thy high perfection,</l>
                     <l>And light my Candle at thy noon-day Sun.</l>
                     <l>I could ſay much were I with Raptures fir'd,</l>
                     <l>Were I, as I muſt think thou art, inſpir'd;</l>
                     <l>For this I know, and muſt ſay't to thy praiſe,</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt gone, in Muſick, unknown wayes,</l>
                     <l>Haſt cut a path where there was none before,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Magellan</hi> traced an unknown ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Thou taught'ſt our Language, firſt, to ſpeak in Tone,</l>
                     <l>Gav'ſt the right accents and proportion;</l>
                     <l>And above all (to ſhew thy excellence)</l>
                     <l>Thou underſtand'ſt good words, and do'ſt ſet ſenſe;</l>
                     <l>Hadſt none to imitate, and few will be</l>
                     <l>Able t' expreſs inimitably thee.</l>
                     <l>Go on then, <hi>Phoebus</hi> like, thine own courſe runne,</l>
                     <l>Fearleſs of being out-ſhin'd by a Mock-Sun.</l>
                     <l>Doggs at the Moon may barke, but never dare</l>
                     <l>Againſt the glorious Sun ſo much as ſtare:</l>
                     <l>Go on ſecure, that <hi>Wilſons</hi> honoured name</l>
                     <l>Shall have, as it deſerves, immortall Fame.</l>
                     <l>Call, O call back thy reſolution</l>
                     <l>Of not compoſing more; Springs allwaies run,</l>
                     <l>The World would ſuffer elſe, and thy great name</l>
                     <l>Be leſſen'd; then do not bound thy boundleſs fame;</l>
                     <l>But, like the Sun, ſtill ſcatter beams of light,</l>
                     <l>Nor the whole World, and thine own worth benight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſure if men do ſingle Ingots prize,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll hugg the Mine where all perfection lies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HENRY LAWES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:36"/>
                  <p>TO THE GLORY OF GOD, THE SACRED MEMORY OF HIS LATE MAIESTIE, AND TO THE RIGHT REVEREND CLERGY OF THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND, <hi>JOHN WILSON,</hi> D. in Muſick, dedicates this his laſt of labours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:37"/>
                  <head>Faults eſcaped in printing, which the curteous Reader is deſired to amend with his penn.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In Cantus ſecundus,</head>
                  <p>SOng 2. l. 6 after the Minnum muſt be a minnum reſt. S. 5. l. 10. to the laſt Crochet wants a prick. S. 6. l. 7. the beginning muſt be a Minnum reſt: S. 10. l. 1. the Crochet muſt be in Alamire which is in F. fa ut. S. 17. l. 18. he Minnum in C-fol-fa ſharp. S. 24, l. 3. next the prick Crochet muſt be two Quavers. <hi>S.</hi> 27. l. 8. next the firſt Minnum muſt be a prick.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="cantus secundus" type="partbook">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:37"/>
                  <head>Pſalterium Carolinum. CANTVS SECVNDVS.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="ode">
                     <head>I</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord haſt made us ſee that pious thoughts Of future reformation for paſt faults, Nor ſatisfie thy juſtice, or prevent Alwaies the ſtroaks of thy dire puniſhment. Our hopes orelaid by ſin
<pb facs="tcp:119890:38"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> on thee depend For pardon, not on our reſolves t'amend. When by vindictive judgements on us layd. Thou haſt thy glory in our ſhame diſplaid. And how' unſafe it is ſhown us by theſe; To dare t'offend, on after hopes to pleaſe: Thy mercies then I truſt the blesſings may Reſtore, which wrong'd we forc'd thee ſnatch away.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:38"/>
                     <head>II</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou whoſe mercies know no bound, Pardon my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant ſin. Death in me the guiltleſs found, Who his refuge ſhould have been. To her ſelf and thee my ſoul, Her tranſ╌gres╌ſion o╌pen laies, Cleanſe me from a guilt ſo foule, And thy mer╌cies I ſhall praiſe. With the crime my heart withſtood, Did my differing hand comply: Yet
<pb facs="tcp:119890:39"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> if bath'd in thy rich blood, Snow my whiteneſs ſhall outvie. Juſtice let me learn of thine, Who for death unjuſtly given, Future dangers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, Into greater now am driven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ode">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou in Heaven, and in my heart, My witneſs art, If to oppreſs the innocent I ever meant; Then
<pb facs="tcp:119890:39"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> let the foe my life confound, And tread my Honours to the ground. The Miſts which cozen humane ſight, Shrink from thy light; The heart and reines thy ſearching eyes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomize. Truth wrapt in darkneſſe loſt in doubt, To day reſtoring O ſhine out.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:40"/>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee I fly thou ſole defence Of my invaded innocence, Who onely canſt the ſtubborn Main, And people more enrag'd reſtrain. The floods, the floods, or'e ſwell their bounds, Danger my threatned ſoul ſurrounds, Mine and my realms iniquity, The tumults tumults of our ſouls
<pb facs="tcp:119890:40"/>'gainſt thee Theſe popular innundations cauſe, That bear down Loyalty and Lawes. But thou to Seas didſt fix a ſhore, And from the Deluge, Earth reſtore, O quell theſe ſalvage Beaſts, And me from their tumultuous Rapines free.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:41"/>
                     <head>V</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my God I ſtill appeal Whoſe all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning eyes reveal, The clouds that humane thoughts conceal. A heart thou gav'ſt me to beſtow Much on my Subjects, which muſt now Learn much from them to undergo. Thy will be done, and ours deny'd, When moſt to thine
<pb facs="tcp:119890:41"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it ſeems ally'd, And theirs who thee pretend their guide: Inſtruct me wiſely to imploy Thy croſſes that my hopes deſtroy, As the ful╌fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of my joy. I raiſed my own fears theirs ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, Unſetled mine, to fix their ſtate, Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence my love with hate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:42"/>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Native freedome Lord preſerve, Which bids our wills thy Will obey; Yet from our Conſcience never ſwerve, Whilſt mens Decrees with Law we weigh, And Reaſon, nor of ought allow, But that to which our judgments bow. Where fixt by thee I did reſide, That Place by
<pb facs="tcp:119890:42"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Subjects forc'd I quitted, Yet for their good my ſelf deny'd, In all to my diſpoſe ſubmitted. Let no demands in Tumults preſt, From my conſent unjuſt power wreſt,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="ode">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thoſe whom thou in Vowes haſt tied, Yet now by diſtance doſt divide, Here or in Heaven u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.
<pb facs="tcp:119890:43"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Defend us from de╌ſpite╌full foes, And by the ſufferings they impoſe, Prepare us for thy ſight. Though in Religion we diſſent, Hear our Devotions joyntly bent Thy ſacred Truth to finde. Love in our equal hearts in╌fuſe, Of thee and him who us t'excuſe His ſinleſs life reſign'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:43"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho vengeance on my wrongs haſt ſhewn, And by my foes, my foes or'ethrown: Let not his fall invite My ſoul by cloſe delight, To make thy juſt revenge her own. Thou haſt reverted on his head The miſchief he for others ſpread, Unwiſh'd, unask'd by me, That all the earth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:44"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> might ſee, Thou didſt my cauſe in judgment plead. I will not, dare not imprecate The like on all that bear me hate. No, to their ſouls diſpence Pardon and penitence. Charg'd with no due af╌fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions weight, Deprive me not of Theams ſo fit for mercy; But their ſins remit Whoſe bold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit climbes, Next thoſe ungratefull crimes, Of which thou me art pleas'd t'acquit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:44"/>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough humane clouds thy Rayes Like lightning glide, No prejudice thy ſentence ſwayes, For knowledge is thy judgments guide. The proud my ſoul oppoſe, And ſlight thy Lawes, Help Lord, for many are my foes: They hate me yet without a cauſe. I never did (thou
<pb facs="tcp:119890:45"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knowſt) theſe broyles begin, In which though I adventure moſt, yet I am certain leaſt to win. But oft deplor'd and ſtrove with care t'avoyd, My life ſuch dangers could not love, Better to ſave than kill employ'd. My other ſuff'rings far their Calumnie outweighs, who tell the world this War (my greateſt croſſe) was rais'd by me. Yet this by ſilence I to men would own, Might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:45"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it their malice ſatis╌fie, whilſt thou my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no╌cence haſt knowne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="ode">
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my God to thee I fly, ſtronger than the enemy, Heaven nor Earth are wiſht by me In compariſon of thee Let me be when all deny'd. More than all by thee ſupply'd. Haſte to help
<pb facs="tcp:119890:46"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thou fail'ſt not thoſe who their truſt in thee repoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="ode">
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternal wiſdom arm'd with might, With truth and right my Reaſon clear; To which ſo make my will adhere, No threats may from their dictates fright. Thou didſt not raiſe me to a Throne, To
<pb facs="tcp:119890:46"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> barr me common li╌ber╌ty. Shall that be nam'd a crime in me, Which others as a vertue own? Unjuſtly they their King deny The free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which all mortals claim: Whilſt even them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves exact the ſame, With partial perti╌na╌ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. To thee I pray who through the Maze Of my own thoughts, and ſuits (like ſnares ſpred to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve my ſoul in cares) Canſt ſurely guide:
<pb facs="tcp:119890:47"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> make plain thy waies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="ode">
                     <head>XII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy mercies Lord, (hence in diſpleaſure fled) On me and my torn Kingdoms I implore; Whoſe loſſe we both too juſtly merited, But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can deſerve thou ſhouldſt reſtore. Thou ſeeſt the cruelty that Chriſtians uſe, In the falſe colours
<pb facs="tcp:119890:47"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Religion dy'd. As if the names of Chriſtians they ſhould loſe, Unleſs they one another cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd. Since we thy Truth and Charity deſpis'd. Error and Hatred now their room poſſeſs, My God, O pardon thoſe thou haſt chaſtis'd. Our wounds with penitential balme redreſſe: Make not our ſufferings leſs in thy eſteeme, and to our Conſcience let our ſinns apPear, As they i'th'
<pb facs="tcp:119890:48"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> mirror of thy judgements ſeem, Which to ſmall crimes are never ſo ſevere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="ode">
                     <head>XIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y troubles, Lord, are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti╌ply'd, O ſuccour the diſtreſt: in ſimpleſt truth thy Servant guide, The wiſeſt Intereſt. From the aſſociate ſtrength of Foes Be thou my juſt defence, Who for the
<pb facs="tcp:119890:48"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Serpents craft depoſe The Doves white innocence. Though to oppreſs me they agree, Combin'd in mutuall aid: Let not my Soul and Honour be To their deceits betray'd. Devotion and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance thou Canſt'in their hearts renew, That him they may reſtore whom now They eager ea╌ger╌ly purſue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:49"/>
                     <head>XIIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord I to thee direct my cries, My ſubjects forward Oaths remit. Quicken their ſence of thoſe firm ties, By Law upon their Conſcience knit, With which no pious, no pretence Of Refor╌ma╌tion can diſpence: Religion owns no injurie, No Sacriledge by thee allow'd, Though mask'd
<pb facs="tcp:119890:49"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> with Hate t'Idolitry. Their zeale diſguiſed fraud uncloud: Things holy 'tis a ſnare to take, And after Vowes enquirie make.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="ode">
                     <head>XV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord thou ſeeſt my wrongs abound. Lions enrag'd my Soul ſurround, With poiſnous words, Their tongues like ſwords, Their teeth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:50"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> like Arrows wound. My foes reproach me all the day, And ſworn deceits together lay; My God, how long Shall they grow ſtrong, Who with vain Lies inveigh? The calumnies which they have ſown On every ſide, to thee are known, Hold not thy peace, Leaſt they increaſe, And bury my Renown. The lyar thou wilt ruinate, The bloody and the falſe do'ſt hate;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:50"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Let my upright Intents, a light Clear as the Sun dilate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="ode">
                     <head>XVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU ſtill the ſame for ever bleſt, Whom mercies infinite inveſt, In various conſtancy expreſt. Thou haſt us with new ſenſe indu'd, Of our old wants; nor ſcorn'ſt renu'd Deſires,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:51"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> in unchang'd words purſu'd. Still let our fix'd Devotions joyn; Our ſuits to thy firm will encline; Our fervent ſpirits move by thine. For thou, in all perfection wiſe, Nor novelty in prayer doſt prize, Nor pious conſtancy deſpiſe. By thy command preferring neither, Left in thy Churches power together, To uſe but not diſparage either.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:51"/>
                     <head>XVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is known, Who haſt appointed me to own Thy ſacred faith's defence. O let me not, of thee forlorn, Againſt my Conſcience be ore╌born, By Floods of violence. Up Lord in thine own cauſe ariſe, Leaſt Schiſme make thy Church its prize, And
<pb facs="tcp:119890:52"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> trample on her power, From thee continued to our time, When Wealth is made her fatall crime; Her ſinn is her fair dower. Whom ſome have plunderd, others wound, The reſt deſerted as they ſound, Or in her ſufferrings joy. May I her hurts and wants relieve, The power which I from thee receive, Teach me for thee t'imploy. To her that love be ſtill ſuſtain'd I owe as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:52"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſtian, though reſtrain'd As King, from all my right. The bounties on thy Church diſplaid, By Providence let none invade, With ſacrilegious might.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="ode">
                     <head>XVIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Peace and Reaſon Lord, Delighting in accord, The wicked, who from Sinn, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:53"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> offer'd grace wouldſt win! Whoſe mercy courts to ſave, Though power to kill thou have, (Our hearts to ſoftneſs woo'd, In our Redeemers blood) Perſwade us to agree Both with our ſelves and thee, As men and Chriſtians ought. Peace often have I ſought, But it no ſooner name Than War my foes proclaime. Our actions never may Deſtructive pasſions ſway. Our
<pb facs="tcp:119890:53"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> judgements clear, that we Thy truth may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee. Our ſtubborn hearts incline, In bonds of Peace to joyn. Our irreligious hate To thee, O disſipate: That to our ſelves remove With interchanged love; The war our ſins have wrought, With peace which Chriſt hath bought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:54"/>
                     <head>XIX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith ready joy O let me, Lord, a gree To be orecome when thou wilt have it ſo: Inſtruct me in the nobleſt vi╌cto╌ry, By patience to ſubdue my ſelf and Foe; Conqueſts, like Chriſt's, a Chriſtian King beſt ſhew. Mould us to pi╌e╌ty betwixt thy hands; Preſt by thy
<pb facs="tcp:119890:54"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> left, ſupported by thy right. Pardon the pride of our ſucceſsfull Bands, And the repinings of our luckleſs fight; When (truſting in our own) denied thy Might. When we are ought or nothing, be thou all; That thy wide glories the whole world may fill, Or in our conqueſt or inglorious fall. Thou know'ſt with what regret I ſuffer ill, From thoſe whoſe good's the ſcope
<pb facs="tcp:119890:55"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of all my will. The ills they force me to inflict, I bear; And in their puniſhments, my own embrace. Victor or vanquiſh'd, ſince a double ſhare Of certain ſuffering doth my hope diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, Grant me a double portion of thy grace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="ode">
                     <head>XX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou who beauty canſt return To them
<pb facs="tcp:119890:55"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> that mourn; And the diſguis'd pretext of Art, To truth convert; O let us not by ſhews beguil'd, Seem pure without, within defil'd. Within, where moſt deform'd we are, Be our firſt care: Then with clear eyes, the Church, we may, And State ſurvey. Our hearts, our ſpirits, Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, That we thy dictates may purſue.
<pb facs="tcp:119890:56"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Upon our foul diſorders, bred By them who (led With rage) to purge us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, With pitty looke. Quench thou the fire that Factions raiſe, From Reformations ſpecious blaze. As their diviſion, Lord, proclaims Their weak bad aims; So let us (in thoſe fires refin'd) In love be join'd; From pasſions freed: bleſt with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:56"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> increaſe Of inward vertue outward peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="ode">
                     <head>XXI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord who by thy wiſe Decree, Doſt our contingency diſpoſe; Make me thy conſtant mercies ſee, In the advantage of my foes. Thou canſt their Counſells turn away, And their de╌vi╌ces ru╌i╌nate: Who all my ſecrets
<pb facs="tcp:119890:57"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> open lay, To worke me in my peoples hate. To thy Omniſcience I repair, Witneſſe with my integrity, How falſe the wreſted Comments are, Which they to what I write apply. The ill, directed by their aim To me, ſo turn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their head, That they may be involv'd in ſhame, And with confuſion overſpread.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:57"/>
                     <head>XXII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou who all ſouls, all conſcien╌ces doſt ſway, To thee I look diſmaid; To thy protection I commit my way, Thou who my life didſt aid, Still in my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe canſt thy ſtrength diſplay. A fierie Pillar in darke nights to me, And with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:58"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy light direct, In ſcorching daies a cloudy Pillar be; And with thy ſhade protect. O let me find both ſun and ſhield in thee. My life I was not by perverſneſſe wrought To hazards thus t'expoſe, But Reaſon, Honour, and Religion taught To guard my ſelf from thoſe, Whoſe impious force to wreſt them from me ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:58"/>
                     <head>XXIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that alone art infinite In good, and greatneſſe; dwel'ſt with me. Weigh'd with thy preſence, life is light, Thy ſervice perfect liberty: Own me for thine, I cannot but be free. As I am man, with reaſon bleſſe; With Zeal as Chriſtian, Right as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:59"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> King. Of outwards ſtript, let me poſſeſſe Thee in the joyes that from thee ſpring; Which gainſt my will no force can from me wring. Let not my pasſion over╌boyle, To fruitleſs rage, or fordid fear; They think him helpleſs whom they foyle: But let thy chearfull light appear, And ſecure freedom ſhall my glories cleer. Befitting my afflicted
<pb facs="tcp:119890:59"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtate, A patient conſtancy beſtow. My ſtrength and hopes are disſipate, My ſelf impriſon'd by the foe: O be not far, leſt they too mighty grow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="ode">
                     <head>XXIV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayers I ſend, The help that others my diſtreſs deny, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:60"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy asſiſtant ſpirit Lord ſupply. To dulneſs life, light to my darkneſs lend. Thou Sun, that beams of righteouſneſs doſt ſpread, Thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſpring of heavenly light and heat, Both warmth and clearneſs in my heart beget, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, and for thy ſervant intercede. Fullneſs, ſufficience, ſavour, thee array; Enough thou comfort art, and company. Thou art my King,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:60"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> my Prieſt and Prophet be; Rule, teach, pray, in me, for me, with me ſtay. Jacob, who ſingly did with thee conteſt In ſacred duell, thee his Second had: He conquer'd, and a blesſing (by thy ayd) From thee, with wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come violence did wreſt. With mercy on thy ſervant be intent, Who his devotions once with them did joyn, Whoſe ſervour might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:61"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> inflame the cold of mine; When to thy Houſe with joy and peace we went.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="ode">
                     <head>XXV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, my King, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eare; My cry, to thee directed, hear. Incens'd, I ſaid, we from thy care Are caſt. Yet thou receiv'ſt my prayer. Thy rigour who can ſatisfy?
<pb facs="tcp:119890:61"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> But to thy mercies Sinners fly. Lord I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my offence, Dilated in my e╌mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. The ſinns I act, or do permit By unimproved power, acquit. Rebellious I to thee became, Now, priſoner to my Subjects am. Yet though reſtrain'd my perſon be, By Grace enlarge my heart to thee; Though <hi>David</hi>'s pi╌e╌ty I want, His griefs I have;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:62"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> his comforts grant</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord, thou ſacred unity, In an undivided Trine, Thoſe combin'd in mercy ſee; Whom thy juſtice doth disjoin. Save me from diſſenting foes, Who my prayers and pity need; And each other now oppoſe, Though to fight with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:62"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> me agreed. All diſcording parties guide To the peace from which they ſtray, Whilſt they ſerve or court a ſide, Not the voice of Law obey. Make me willingly to go Where thy providence will lead: And the change of things be╌low, In thy conſtant preſence read. Make me by thy skillfull hand, Such as thou wouldſt have me be; Then waft me ſafely
<pb facs="tcp:119890:63"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to that land, Where peace e╌ver dwells with thee. Spare our Cities (Lord) impure Through their wealth and plenty made; In their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſecure, By ſecurity betrai'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that fill'ſt Heaven and earth, O King of Kings, In whom no death, whence life
<pb facs="tcp:119890:63"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> eternal ſprings. Who canſt our ſouls unto the yawning Grave, Juſtly condemn or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci╌ful╌ly ſave. Better be dead t'our ſelves, in thee ſurvive; Than rob'd of thee, and to our ſelves a╌live. O let the bit╌ter means that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate My fall, thy comforts in my ſoul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. If thou art with me, fear ſhall not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail Though I ſhould walk along death's ſhady
<pb facs="tcp:119890:64"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> vale. Weak mortall man may with his fate contend, But 'tis thy grace muſt ſtrength to vanquiſh lend. Thou know'ſt, as man, what 'tis to dye, with me, Teach me by Death to live, my God, with thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:64"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:65"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:65"/>
                  <p>Pſalterium Carolinum. THE DEVOTIONS OF HIS SACRED MAJESTIE IN HIS SOLITUDES AND SUFFERINGS, Rendred in Verſe.</p>
                  <p>Set to Muſick for 3. Voices and an Organ, or Theorbo, By <hi>John Wilſon</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. and Muſick Profeſſor of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device? (not in McKerrow): angel standing with one foot on a bell, blowing a trumpet</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <unclear>VI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>VENERANDA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>SONES</unclear>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martin</hi> and <hi>James Alleſtrey,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bell in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:66"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:66"/>
                  <p>TO THE GLORY OF GOD, THE SACRED MEMORY OF HIS LATE MAIESTIE, AND TO THE RIGHT REVEREND CLERGY OF THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND, <hi>JOHN WILSON,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. in Muſick, dedicates this his laſt of labours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:67"/>
                  <head>Faults eſcaped in printing, which the curteous Reader is deſired to amend with his penn.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In the Baſe,</head>
                  <p>SOng 13. line 7. the Crochet in B-mie muſt be in Ef-fa-ut. S. 24. l. 2. a prick by the Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:67"/>
                  <head>To his friend (and formerly, fellow-ſervant to his late Majeſtie) <hi>JOHN WILSON</hi> Dr. in Muſick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I do love thee, friend, I now would ſhew it,</l>
                     <l>And do't in Rhime too, though I am no Poet;</l>
                     <l>Yet all that I could ſay, would but appear</l>
                     <l>Fruitleſs, and inſignificantly here,</l>
                     <l>Since nothing, truly, can thy worth explain,</l>
                     <l>But the compoſures of thine own rich brain.</l>
                     <l>Thou need'ſt no Trumpet to proclaim thy Fame,</l>
                     <l>Thy Lyre moſt ſweetly warbles forth thy name;</l>
                     <l>Which every one muſt needs admire that hears,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he have nor Soul, nor Senſe, nor Ears.</l>
                     <l>This tribute all muſt pay, but none can raiſe</l>
                     <l>(Unleſs he have an equall skill) thy praiſe.</l>
                     <l>From long acquaintance and experience, I</l>
                     <l>Could tell the World thy known integrity;</l>
                     <l>Unto thy Friend thy true and honeſt heart,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n mind, good nature, all, but thy great Art,</l>
                     <l>Which I but dully underſtand; who do</l>
                     <l>To ſhadow't out, muſt have expreſsions too,</l>
                     <l>(If with thy merits they proportion keep)</l>
                     <l>As high, and apt, as is thy judgement deep.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus Diamonds Diamonds cut, Kings judge of Kings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Art cann't be prais'd enough by artleſs things.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:68"/>
                     <l>Excuſe me then, if I have no deſigns</l>
                     <l>Impoſsible, and needleſs by theſe lines,</l>
                     <l>So low, to raiſe thy high perfection,</l>
                     <l>And light my Candle at thy noon-day Sun:</l>
                     <l>I could ſay much were I with Raptures fir'd,</l>
                     <l>Were I, as I muſt think thou art, inſpir'd;</l>
                     <l>For this I know, and muſt ſay't to thy praiſe,</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt gone, in Muſick, unknown wayes,</l>
                     <l>Haſt cut a path where there was none before,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Magellan</hi> traced an unknown ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Thou taught'ſt our Language, firſt, to ſpeak in Tone,</l>
                     <l>Gavſt the right accents and proportion;</l>
                     <l>And above all (to ſhew thy excellence)</l>
                     <l>Thou underſtand'ſt good words, and do'ſt ſet ſenſe;</l>
                     <l>Hadſt none to imitate, and few will be</l>
                     <l>Able t' expreſs inimitably thee.</l>
                     <l>Go on then, <hi>Phoebus</hi> like, thine own courſe runne,</l>
                     <l>Fearleſs of being out-ſhin'd by a Mock-Sun.</l>
                     <l>Doggs at the Moon may barke, but never dare</l>
                     <l>Againſt the glorious Sun ſo much as ſtare:</l>
                     <l>Go on ſecure, that <hi>Wilſons</hi> honoured name</l>
                     <l>Shall have, as it deſerves, immortall Fame.</l>
                     <l>Call, O call back thy reſolution</l>
                     <l>Of not compoſing more; Springs allwaies run,</l>
                     <l>The World would ſuffer elſe, and thy great name</l>
                     <l>Be leſſen'd; then do not bound thy boundleſs fame;</l>
                     <l>But, like the Sun, ſtill ſcatter beams of light,</l>
                     <l>Nor the whole World, and thine own worth benight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſure if men do ſingle Ingots prize,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll hugg the Mine where all perfection lies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="bass" type="partbook">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:68"/>
                  <head>Pſalterium Carolinum. CANTVS SECVNDVS.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="ode">
                     <head>I</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord haſt made us ſee that pious thoughts Of future reformation for paſt faults, Nor ſatisfie thy juſtice, or prevent Alwaies the ſtroaks of thy dire puniſhment. Our hopes orelaid by ſin
<pb facs="tcp:119890:69"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> on thee depend For pardon, not on our reſolves t'amend. When by vindictive judgements on us layd. Thou haſt thy glory in our ſhame diſplaid. And how' unſafe it is ſhown us by theſe; To dare t'offend, on after hopes to pleaſe: Thy mercies then I truſt the blesſings may Reſtore, which wrong'd we forc'd thee ſnatch away.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:69"/>
                     <head>II</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou whoſe mercies know no bound, Pardon my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliant ſin. Death in me the guiltleſs found, Who his refuge ſhould have been. To her ſelf and thee my ſoul, Her tranſ╌gres╌ſion o╌pen laies Cleanſe me from a guilt ſo foule, And thy mer╌cies I ſhall praiſe. With the crime my heart withſtood, Did my differing hand comply: Yet
<pb facs="tcp:119890:70"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> if bath'd in thy rich blood, Snow my whiteneſs ſhall outvie. Juſtice let me learn of thine, Who for death unjuſtly given, Future dangers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, Into greater now am driven.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ode">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou in Heaven, and in my heart, My witneſs art, If to oppreſs the innocent I ever meant; Then
<pb facs="tcp:119890:70"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> let my foe my life confound, And tread my Honours to the ground. The Miſts which cozen humane ſight, Shrink from thy light; The heart and reines thy ſearching eyes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomize. Truth wrapt in darkneſſe loſt in doubt, To day reſtoring O ſhine out.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:71"/>
                     <head>IIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee I fly thou ſole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence Of my invaded innocence, Who onely canſt the ſtubborn Main, And people more enrag'd reſtrain. The floods, the floods, or'e ſwell their bounds, Danger my threatned ſoul ſurrounds, Mine and my realms iniquity, The tumults tumults of our ſouls
<pb facs="tcp:119890:71"/>'gainſt thee Theſe popular innundations cauſe, That bear down Loyalty and Lawes. But thou to Seas didſt fix a ſhore, And from the Deluge, Earth reſtore, O quell theſe ſalvage Beaſts, And me from their tumultuous Rapines free.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:72"/>
                     <head>V</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my God I ſtill appeal Whoſe all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning eyes reveal, The clouds that humane thoughts conceal. A heart thou gav'ſt me to beſtow Much on my Subjects, which muſt now Learn much from them to undergo. Thy will be done, and ours deny'd, When moſt to thine
<pb facs="tcp:119890:72"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it ſeems ally'd, And theirs who thee pretend their guide: Inſtruct me wiſely to imploy The croſſes that my hopes deſtroy, As the ful╌fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of my joy. I rais'd my own fears theirs t'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, Unſetled mine, to fix their ſtate, Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence my love with hate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:73"/>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Native freedome Lord preſerve, Which bids our wills thy Will obey; Yet from our Conſcience never ſwerve, Whilſt mens De╌crees with Law we weigh, And Reaſon, nor of ought allow, But that to which our judgments bow. Where fix'd by thee I did reſide, That Place by
<pb facs="tcp:119890:73"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Subjects forc'd I quitted, Yet for their good my ſelf deny'd, In all to my diſpoſe ſubmitted. Let no demands in Tumults preſt, From my conſent unjuſt power wreſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="ode">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thoſe whom thou in Vowes haſt tied, Yet now by diſtance doſt divide, Here or in Heaven u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.
<pb facs="tcp:119890:74"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Defend us from de╌ſpite╌full foes, And by the ſufferings they impoſe, Prepare us for thy ſight. Though in Religion we diſſent, Hear our Devotions joyntly bent Thy ſacred Truth to finde. Love in our equal hearts in╌fuſe, Of thee and him who us t'excuſe His ſinleſs life reſign'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:74"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho vengeance on my wrongs haſt ſhewn, And by my foes, my foes or'ethrown: Let not his fall invite My ſoul by cloſe delight, To make thy juſt revenge her own. Thou haſt reverted on his head The miſchief he for others ſpread, Unwiſh'd, unask'd by me, That all the earth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:75"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> might ſee, Thou didſt my cauſe in judgment plead. I will not, dare not imprecate The like on all that bear me hate. No, to their ſouls diſpence Pardon and penitence. Charg'd with no due af╌fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions weight, Deprive me not of Theams ſo fit for mercy; But their ſins remit, Whoſe bold de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit climbes, Next thoſe ungratefull crimes, Of which thou me art pleas'd t'acquit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:75"/>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough humane clouds thy Rayes, Like lightning glide, No prejudice thy ſentence ſwayes, For knowledge is thy judgments guide. The proud my ſoul oppoſe, And ſlight thy Lawes, Help Lord, for many are my foes: They hate me yet without a cauſe. I never did (thou knoweſt)
<pb facs="tcp:119890:76"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> knowſt) theſe broyles begin, In which though I adventure moſt, yet I am certain leaſt to win. But oft deplor'd and ſtrove with care t'avoyd, My life ſuch dangers could not love, Better to ſave than kill employ'd. My other ſuff'rings far their Calumnie outweighs, who tell the world this War (my greateſt croſſe) was rais'd by me. Yet this by ſilence I to men would own, Might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:76"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> it their malice ſatis╌fie, whilſt thou my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no╌cence haſt knowne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="ode">
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my God to thee I fly, ſtronger than the enemy, Heaven nor Earth are wiſht by me In compariſon of thee; Let me be, when all deny'd, More than all by thee ſupply'd. Haſte to help,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:77"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thou fail'ſt not thoſe who their truſt in thee repoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="ode">
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternal wiſdom arm'd with might, With truth and right my Reaſon clear; To which ſo make my will adhere, No threats may from their dictates fright. Thou didſt not raiſe me to a Throne, To
<pb facs="tcp:119890:77"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> barr me common li╌ber╌ty. Shall that be nam'd a crime in me, Which others as a vertue own? Unjuſtly they their King deny The free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which all mortals claim: Whilſt even them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves exact the ſame, With partial perti╌na╌ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. To thee I pray who through the Maze Of my own thoughts, and ſuits (like ſnares ſpred to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve my ſoul in cares) Canſt ſurely guide:
<pb facs="tcp:119890:78"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> make plain thy waies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="ode">
                     <head>XII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy mercies Lord, (hence in diſpleaſure fled) On me and my torn Kingdoms I implore; Whoſe loſſe we both too juſtly merited, But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can deſerve thou ſhouldſt reſtore. Thou ſeeſt the cruelty that Chriſtians uſe, In the falſe colours
<pb facs="tcp:119890:78"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Religion dy'd, As if the name of Chriſtians they ſhould loſe, Unleſs they one another cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd. Since we thy Truth and Charity deſpis'd, Error and Hatred now their room poſſeſs; My God, O pardon thoſe thou haſt chaſtis'd, Our wounds with penitential balme redreſſe: Make not our ſufferings leſs in thy eſteeme, And to our Conſcience let our ſinns appear, As they i'th'
<pb facs="tcp:119890:79"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> mirror of thy judgements ſeem, Which to ſmall crimes are never ſo ſevere.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="ode">
                     <head>XIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y troubles, Lord, are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti╌ply'd, O ſuccour the diſtreſt: in ſimpleſt truth thy Servant guide, The wiſeſt Intereſt. From the aſſociate ſtrength of Foes Be thou my juſt defence, Who for the
<pb facs="tcp:119890:79"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Serpents craft depoſe The Doves white innocence. Though to oppreſs me they agree, Combin'd in mutuall aid: Let not my Soul and Honours be To their deceits betray'd. Devotion and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance thou Canſt in their hearts renew, That him they may reſtore whom now They eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ea╌ger╌ly purſue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:80"/>
                     <head>XIIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord I to thee direct my cries, My ſubjects forward Oaths remit; Quicken their ſence of thoſe firm ties, By Law upon their Conſcience knit: With which no pious, no pretence Of Refor╌ma╌tion can diſpence: Religion owns no injurie, No Sacriledge by thee allow'd, Though mask'd
<pb facs="tcp:119890:80"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> with Hate t'Idolitry. Their zeale diſguiſed fraud uncloud: Things holy 'tis a ſnare to take, And after Vowes enquirie make.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="ode">
                     <head>XV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord thou ſeeſt my wrongs abound. Lions enrag'd my Soul ſurround, With poiſnous words, Their tongues like ſwords, Their teeth
<pb facs="tcp:119890:81"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> like Arrows wound. My foes reproach me all the day, And ſworn deceits together lay; My God, how long Shall they grow ſtrong, Who with vain Lies inveigh? The calumnies which they have ſown On every ſide, to thee are known, Hold not thy peace, Leaſt they increaſe, And bury my Renown. The lyar thou wilt ruinate, The bloody and the falſe do'ſt hate;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:81"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Let my upright Intents, a light Clear as the Sun dilate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="ode">
                     <head>XVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOU ſtill the ſame for ever bleſt, Whom mercies infinite inveſt, In various conſtancy expreſt. Thou haſt us with new ſenſe indu'd, Of our old wants; nor ſcorn'ſt renu'd Deſires,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:82"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> in unchang'd words purſu'd. Still let our fix'd Devotions joyn; Our ſuits to thy firm will encline; Our fervent ſpirits move by thine. For thou, in all perfection wiſe, Nor novelty in prayer doſt prize, Nor pious conſtancy deſpiſe. By thy command preferring neither, Left in thy Churches power together, To uſe but not diſparage either.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:82"/>
                     <head>XVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is known, Who haſt appointed me to own Thy ſacred faith's defence. O let me not, of thee forlorn, Againſt my Conſcience be ore╌born, By Floods of violence. Up Lord in thine own cauſe ariſe, Leaſt Schiſme make thy Church its prize, And
<pb facs="tcp:119890:83"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> trample on her power, From thee continued to our time, When Wealth is made her fatall crime; Her ſinn is her fair dower. Whom ſome have plunderd, others wound, The reſt deſerted as they found, Or in her ſufferrings joy. May I her hurts and wants relieve, The power which I from thee receive, Teach me for thee t'imploy. To her that love be ſtill ſuſtain'd I owe as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:83"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſtian, though reſtrain'd As King, from all my right. The bounties on thy Church diſplaid, By Providence let none invade, With ſa╌cri╌le╌gi╌ous might.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="ode">
                     <head>XVIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Peace and Reaſon Lord, Delighting in accord, The wicked, who from Sinn, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:84"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> offer'd grace wouldſt win! Whoſe mercy courts to ſave, Though power to kill thou have, (Our hearts to ſoftneſs woo'd, In our Redeemers blood) Perſwade us to agree Both with our ſelves and thee, As men and Chriſtians ought. Peace often have I ſought, But it no ſooner name Than War my foes proclaime. Our actions never may Deſtructive pasſions ſway. Our
<pb facs="tcp:119890:84"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> judgements clear, that we Thy truth may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee. Our ſtubborn hearts incline, In bonds of Peace to joyn. Our irreligious hate To thee, O disſipate: That to our ſelves remove With interchanged love, The war our ſins have wrought, With peace which Chriſt hath bought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:85"/>
                     <head>XIX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith ready joy O let me, Lord, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree To be orecome when thou wilt have it ſo: Inſtruct me in the nobleſt vi╌cto╌ry, By patience to ſubdue my ſelf and Foe; Conqueſts, like Chriſt's, a Chriſtian King beſt ſhew. Mould us to pi╌e╌ty betwixt thy hands; Preſt by thy
<pb facs="tcp:119890:85"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> left, ſupported by thy right. Pardon the pride of our ſucceſsfull Bands, And the repinings of our luckleſs fight; When (truſting in our own) denied thy Might. When we are ought or nothing, be thou all; That thy wide glories the whole world may fill, Or in our conqueſt or inglorious fall. Thou know'ſt with what regret I ſuffer ill, From thoſe whoſe good's the ſcope
<pb facs="tcp:119890:86"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> of all my will. The ills they force me to inflict, I bear; And in their puniſhments, my own embrace. Victor or vanquiſh'd, ſince a double ſhare Of certain ſuffering doth my hope diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, Grant me a double portion of thy grace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="ode">
                     <head>XX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord thou who beauty canſt return To them
<pb facs="tcp:119890:86"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> that mourn; And the diſguis'd pretext of Art, To truth convert; O let us not by ſhews beguil'd, Seem pure without, within defil'd. Within, where moſt deform'd we are, Be our firſt care: Then with clear eyes, the Church, we may, And State ſurvey. Our hearts; our ſpirits, Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, That we thy dictates may purſue.
<pb facs="tcp:119890:87"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Upon our foul diſorders, bred By them who (led With rage) to purge us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, With pitty looke. Quench thou the fire that Factions raiſe, From Reformations ſpecious blaze. As their diviſion, Lord, proclaims Their weak bad aims; So let us (in thoſe fires refin'd) In love be join'd; From pasſions freed, bleſt with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:87"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> increaſe Of inward vertue outward peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="ode">
                     <head>XXI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord who by thy wiſe Decree, Doſt our contingency diſpoſe; Make me thy conſtant mercies ſee, In the advantage of my foes. Thou canſt their Counſells turn away, And their de╌vi. ces ru╌i╌nate: Who all my ſecrets
<pb facs="tcp:119890:88"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> open lay, To worke me in my peoples hate. To thy Omniſcience I repair, Witneſſe with my integrity, How falſe the wreſted Comments are, Which they to what I write apply. The ill, directed by their aim To me, ſo turn up. on their head, That they may be involv'd in ſhame, And with con╌fu╌ſi╌on overſpread.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:88"/>
                     <head>XXII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou who all ſouls, all conſcien╌ces doſt ſway, To thee I look diſmaid; To thy protection I commit my way, Thou who my life didſt aid, Still in my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe canſt thy ſtrength diſplay. A fierie Pillar in darke nights to me, And with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:89"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy light direct, In ſcorching daies a cloudy Pillar be; And with thy ſhade protect. O let me find both ſun and ſhield in thee. My life I was not by perverſneſſe wrought To hazards thus t'expoſe, But Reaſon, Honour, and Religion taught. To guard myſelf from thoſe, Whoſe impious force to wreſt them from me ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:89"/>
                     <head>XXIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that alone art infinite In good, and greatneſſe, dwel'ſt with me; Weigh'd with thy preſence, life is light, Thy ſervice perfect liberty: Own me for thine, I cannot but be free. As I am man, with reaſon bleſſe, With Zeal as Chriſtian, Right as
<pb facs="tcp:119890:90"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> King. Of outwards ſtript, let me poſſeſſe Thee in the joyes that from thee ſpring; Which gainſt my will no force can from me wring. Let not my pasſion over╌boyle, To fruitleſs rage, or ſordid fear; They think him helpleſs whom they foyle: But let thy chearfull light appear, And ſecure freedom ſhall my glories cleer. Befitting my afflicted
<pb facs="tcp:119890:90"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſtate, A patient conſtancy beſtow. My ſtrength and hopes are disſipate, My ſelf impriſon'd by the foe: O be not far, leſt they too mighty grow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="ode">
                     <head>XXIV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O thee my ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayers I ſend, The help that others my diſtreſs deny, With
<pb facs="tcp:119890:91"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> thy asſiſtant ſpirit Lord ſupply. To dulneſs life, light to my darkneſs lend. Thou Sun, that beams of righteouſneſs doſt ſpread, Thou ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſpring of heavenly light and heat, Both warmth and clearneſs in my heart beget, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, and for thy ſervant intercede. Fullneſs, ſufficience, favour, thee array; Enough thou comfort art, and company. Thou art my King,
<pb facs="tcp:119890:91"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> my Prieſt and Prophet be; Rule, teach, pray, in me, for me, with me ſtay. Jacob, who ſingly did with thee conteſt In ſacred duell, thee his Second had: He conquer'd, and a blesſing (by thy ayd) From thee, with wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come violence did wreſt. With mercy on thy ſervant be intent, Who his devotions once with them did joyn, Whoſe ſervour might
<pb facs="tcp:119890:92"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> inflame the cold of mine; When to thy Houſe with joy and peace we went.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="ode">
                     <head>XXV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y God, my King, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine eare; My cry, to thee directed, hear. Incens'd, I ſaid, we from thy care Are caſt. Yet thou receiv'ſt my prayer. Thy rigour who can ſatisfy?
<pb facs="tcp:119890:92"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> But to thy mercies Sinners fly. Lord I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my offence, Dilated in my e╌mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. The ſinns I act, or do permit By unimproved power, acquit. Rebellious I to thee became, Now, priſoner to my Subjects am. Yet though reſtrain'd my perſon be, By Grace enlarge my heart to thee; Though <hi>David</hi>'s pi╌e╌ty I want, His griefs I have;
<pb facs="tcp:119890:93"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> his comforts grant</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord, thou ſacred unity, In an undivided Trine, Thoſe combin'd in mercy ſee; Whom thy juſtice doth disjoin. Save me from diſſenting foes, Who my prayers and pity need; And each other now oppoſe, Though to fight with
<pb facs="tcp:119890:93"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> me agreed. All diſcording parties guide To the peace from which they ſtray, Whilſt they ſerve or court a ſide, Not the voice of Law obey. Make me willingly to go Where thy providence will lead: And the change of things be╌low, In thy conſtant preſence read. Make me by thy skillfull hand, Such as thou wouldſt have me be; Then waft me ſafely
<pb facs="tcp:119890:94"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to that land, Where peace e╌ver dwells with thee. Spare our Cities (Lord) impure Through their wealth and plenty made; In their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſecure, By ſe╌cu╌ri╌ty betrai'd.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="ode">
                     <head>XXVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou that fill'ſt Heaven and earth, O King of Kings, In whom no death, whence life
<pb facs="tcp:119890:94"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> eternal ſprings. Who canſt our ſouls unto the yawning Grave, Juſtly condemn or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci╌ful╌ly ſave. Better be dead t'our ſelves, in thee ſurvive; Than rob'd of thee, and to our ſelves a╌live. O let the bitter means that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate My fall, thy comforts in my ſoul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. If thou art with me, fear ſhall not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſail Though I ſhould walk along death's ſhady
<pb facs="tcp:119890:95"/>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> vale. Weak mortall man may with his fate contend, But 'tis thy grace muſt ſtrength to vanquiſh lend. Thou know'ſt, as man, what 'tis to dye, with me, Teach me by Death to live, my God, with thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:95"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:96"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:96"/>
                  <p>Pſalterium Carolinum. THE DEVOTIONS OF HIS SACRED MAJESTIE IN HIS SOLITUDES AND SUFFERINGS, Rendred in Verſe.</p>
                  <p>Set to Muſick for 3 Voices and an Organ, or Theorbo, By <hi>John Wilſon</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. and Muſick Profeſſor of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's device? (not in McKerrow): angel standing with one foot on a bell, blowing a trumpet</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <unclear>VI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>VENERANDA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>SONES</unclear>
                     </head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martin</hi> and <hi>James Alleſtrey,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bell in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:97"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:97"/>
                  <p>TO THE GLORY OF GOD, THE SACRED MEMORY OF HIS LATE MAIESTIE, AND TO THE RIGHT REVEREND CLERGY OF THE CHURCH OF ENGLAND, <hi>JOHN WILSON,</hi> D. in Muſick, dedicates this his laſt of labours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:98"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:98"/>
                  <head>To his friend (and formerly, fellow-ſervant to his late Majeſtie) <hi>JOHN WILSON</hi> Dr. in Muſick.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I do love thee, friend, I now would ſhew it,</l>
                     <l>And do't in Rhime too, though I am no Poet;</l>
                     <l>Yet all that I could ſay, would but appear</l>
                     <l>Fruitleſs, and inſignificantly here,</l>
                     <l>Since nothing, truly, can thy worth explain,</l>
                     <l>But the compoſures of thine own rich brain.</l>
                     <l>Thou need'ſt no Trumpet to proclaim thy Fame,</l>
                     <l>Thy Lyre moſt ſweetly warbles forth thy name;</l>
                     <l>Which every one muſt needs admire that hears,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he have nor Soul, nor Senſe, nor Ears.</l>
                     <l>This tribute all muſt pay, but none can raiſe</l>
                     <l>(Unleſs he have an equall skill) thy praiſe.</l>
                     <l>From long acquaintance and experience, I</l>
                     <l>Could tell the World thy known integrity;</l>
                     <l>Unto thy Friend thy true and honeſt heart,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n mind, good nature, all, but thy great Art,</l>
                     <l>Which I but dully underſtand; who do</l>
                     <l>To ſhadow't out, muſt have expreſsions too,</l>
                     <l>(If with thy merits they proportion keep)</l>
                     <l>As high, and apt, as is thy judgement deep.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus Diamonds Diamonds cut, Kings judge of Kings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Art cann't be prais'd enough by artleſs thigns.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:99"/>
                     <l>Excuſe me then, if I have no deſigns</l>
                     <l>Impoſsible, and needleſs by theſe lines,</l>
                     <l>So low, to raiſe thy high perfection,</l>
                     <l>And light my Candle at thy noon-day Sun.</l>
                     <l>I could ſay much were I with Raptures fir'd,</l>
                     <l>Were I, as I muſt think thou art, inſpir'd;</l>
                     <l>For this I know, and muſt ſay't to thy praiſe,</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt gone, in Muſick, unknown wayes,</l>
                     <l>Haſt cut a path where there was none before,</l>
                     <l>Like <hi>Magellan</hi> traced an unknown ſhore.</l>
                     <l>Thou taught'ſt our Language, firſt, to ſpeak in Tone,</l>
                     <l>Gav'ſt the right accents and proportion;</l>
                     <l>And above all (to ſhew thy excellence)</l>
                     <l>Thou underſtand'ſt good words, and do'ſt ſet ſenſe;</l>
                     <l>Hadſt none to imitate, and few will be</l>
                     <l>Able t' expreſs inimitably thee.</l>
                     <l>Go on then, <hi>Phoebus</hi> like, thine own courſe runne</l>
                     <l>Fearleſs of being out-ſhin'd by a Mock-Sun.</l>
                     <l>Doggs at the Moon may barke, but never dare</l>
                     <l>Againſt the glorious Sun ſo much as ſtare:</l>
                     <l>Go on ſecure, that <hi>Wilſons</hi> honoured name</l>
                     <l>Shall have, as it deſerves, immortall Fame.</l>
                     <l>Call, O call back thy reſolution</l>
                     <l>Of not compoſing more; Springs allwaies run,</l>
                     <l>The World would ſuffer elſe, and thy great name</l>
                     <l>Be leſſen'd; then do not bound thy boundleſs fame;</l>
                     <l>But, like the Sun, ſtill ſcatter beams of light,</l>
                     <l>Nor the whole World, and thine own worth benight</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſure if men do ſingle Ingots prize,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll hugg the Mine where all perfection lies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HENRY LAWES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="basso continuo" type="instrumental_part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:99"/>
                  <head>Pſalterium Carolinum. BASSO CONTINVO</head>
                  <div n="1" type="ode">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou Lord haſt made us ſee &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:100"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:100"/>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou whoſe mercies &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:101"/>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lord thou in Heaven &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:101"/>
                     <head>IIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> To thee I fly &amp;.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:102"/>
                     <head>V</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> To thee my God &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:102"/>
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Our native freedom &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:103"/>
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lord thoſe whom thou &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:103"/>
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Who vengeance on &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:104"/>
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Through human Clouds &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:104"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:105"/>
                     <head>X.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> O my God to thee I fly &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:105"/>
                     <head>XI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Eternall wiſedome &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:106"/>
                     <head>XII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thy mercies Lord &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:106"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:107"/>
                     <head>XIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> My troubles Lord &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:107"/>
                     <head>XIV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lord I to thee direct my cries &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:108"/>
                     <head>XV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> O Lord thou ſeeſt my wrongs &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:108"/>
                     <head>XVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou ſtill the ſame &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:109"/>
                     <head>XVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> To thee my uprightneſs is &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:109"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:110"/>
                     <head>XVIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Of Peace and Reaſon Lord, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:110"/>
                     <head>XIX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> With ready Ioy &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:111"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:111"/>
                     <head>XX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lord thou who beauty canſt &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:112"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:112"/>
                     <head>XXI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou Lord who by thy wiſe &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:113"/>
                     <head>XXII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou who all Souls, all Conſciences &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:113"/>
                     <head>XXIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou that alone art infinite &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:114"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:114"/>
                     <head>XXIV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> To thee my ſolitary pray'rs &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:115"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:115"/>
                     <head>XXV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> My God, my King, incline &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:116"/>
                     <head>XXVI.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lord thou ſacred Unity &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:116"/>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:117"/>
                     <head>XXVII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Thou that fill'ſt Heaven &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:117"/>
                  <p>Pſalterium Carolinum. THE DEVOTIONS OF HIS <hi>SACRED MAJESTY</hi> CHARLES THE FIRST IN HIS SOLITUDES AND SUFFERINGS;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rendred in Verſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martin, James Alleſtry,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Dicas,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bell in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1660.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:118"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:118"/>
                  <head>TO HIS SACRED MAJESTY CHARLES, THE SECOND.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Pſalmes of</hi> David <hi>have been continued in verſe through many Languages; in theſe your Majeſty's Royal Father, (a Perſon of like Dignity, Sufferings and Piety,) breaths forth, (for ſo he calls them) the comforts of</hi> David. <hi>The Parallel gave occaſion to this attempt; and that inacceſſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Language, in which they were firſt cloath'd, will juſtifie to the World, that there could not be any poſſible encouragement to this undertaking, more than that of a pious Duty to the ſacred memory of the Author; and a particular Devotion to declare my ſelf,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Loyal and Obedient Subject, THO. STANLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text_of_poems">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:119"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:119"/>
                  <head>Pſalterium Carolinum.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE. I. <hi>Vpon his Majeſtie's calling the Parliament.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou Lord, haſt made us ſee, that pious thoughts</l>
                        <l>Of future reformation for paſt faults;</l>
                        <l>Nor ſatisfie thy juſtice; or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</l>
                        <l>Alwaies the ſtrokes of thy dire pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</l>
                        <l>Our hopes, ore-laid by ſin, on thee depend</l>
                        <l>For pardon, not on our Reſolves t'amend,</l>
                        <l>When by vindictive judgements on us laid,</l>
                        <l>Thou haſt thy glory in our ſhame diſplaid:</l>
                        <l>And how unſafe it is, ſhewn us by theſe,</l>
                        <l>To dare t' offend, on after hopes to pleaſe.</l>
                        <l>Thy mercies then (I truſt) the bleſsings may</l>
                        <l>Reſtore, which wrong'd, we forc'd thee ſnatch away.</l>
                        <l>Who early penitence for ſin deni'd,</l>
                        <l>Now mourn for remedies too late apply'd.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:120"/>
                        <l>Yet as my Aims were right, I not repent</l>
                        <l>That I this later Councell did convent.</l>
                        <l>Th'inſuing Miſeries have, for our ſin,</l>
                        <l>The ſad effects of thy juſt anger bin;</l>
                        <l>And through thy mercy may preparatives</l>
                        <l>Of future bleſsings be, and better lives.</l>
                        <l>Stript of all elſe, teach us by them to thrive;</l>
                        <l>That as thy Staff, thy Rod may comfort give.</l>
                        <l>If with afflictions, patience thou beſtow,</l>
                        <l>The ſtroaks are of a Father, not a Foe.</l>
                        <l>Nor ſhall I then the ills this Councell wrought</l>
                        <l>Repent; by them to true repentance brought.</l>
                        <l>Our ſufferings with thy Grace, far more we prize,</l>
                        <l>Than our own peace with our impieties.</l>
                        <l>Sole Good and Wiſe, our hearts as Councells ſteare;</l>
                        <l>That the worſt things we from thy juſtice bear</l>
                        <l>To better, by thy mercy us inure,</l>
                        <l>Poyſon'd with Antidotes, with poiſon cure.</l>
                        <l>So we by ſins of Peace, to War inclin'd,</l>
                        <l>Through this ſad war, thy happy peace may finde.</l>
                        <l>Whilſt I (though troubles here perplex my raign)</l>
                        <l>May in my heart, and in thy Heav'n attain</l>
                        <l>That Crown of Peace which Chriſt hath bought, &amp; thou</l>
                        <l>Wilt on thy ſervant for his ſake beſtow.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE II. <hi>Vpon the Earl of</hi> Strafford's <hi>death.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou whoſe mercies know no bound,</l>
                        <l>Pardon my compliant ſin.</l>
                        <l>Death in me the guiltleſs found,</l>
                        <l>Who his Refuge ſhould have bin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:120"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To her ſelf and thee my Soul,</l>
                        <l>Her tranſgreſsion open laies;</l>
                        <l>Cleanſe me from a guilt ſo foul,</l>
                        <l>And thy mercies I ſhall praiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With the crime, my heart withſtood,</l>
                        <l>Did my differing hand comply;</l>
                        <l>Yet if bath'd in thy rich blood,</l>
                        <l>Snow my whiteneſſe ſhall outvy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Juſtice let me learn of thine,</l>
                        <l>Who for death unjuſtly given;</l>
                        <l>Future dangers to decline,</l>
                        <l>Into greater now am driven.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor by partiall judgements ſway'd</l>
                        <l>Let me with thy will diſpence.</l>
                        <l>Once (too oft) I was betray'd</l>
                        <l>Man to appeaſe and thee incenſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor brib'd by Intereſt let me,</l>
                        <l>My miſguided heart withdraw</l>
                        <l>From my conſcience and from thee:</l>
                        <l>Thou my Iudge, and that my Law.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To thy joy my Soul unite,</l>
                        <l>And my ready will ſubmit</l>
                        <l>To thy ſpirits ſaving light,</l>
                        <l>Truth my heart and actions knit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:121"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord to the interceding Voice,</l>
                        <l>Of my Saviours blood encline.</l>
                        <l>O make me and mine rejoyce,</l>
                        <l>And the broken bones rejoyn.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE III. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties going to the houſe of Commons.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOrd thou in Heav'n and in my heart</l>
                        <l>My witneſſe art,</l>
                        <l>If to oppreſſe the Innocent</l>
                        <l>I ever meant,</l>
                        <l>Then let the Foe my life confound,</l>
                        <l>And tread my Honours to the ground.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The miſts which cozen humane ſight</l>
                        <l>Shrink from thy light;</l>
                        <l>The Heart and Reins thy ſearching eies</l>
                        <l>Anatomize;</l>
                        <l>Truth wrapt in darkneſſe, loſt in doubt,</l>
                        <l>To day reſtoring; O ſhine out.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor guilty in the ills I bear</l>
                        <l>Let me appear;</l>
                        <l>Though innocence from their ſucceſs</l>
                        <l>My foes profeſs,</l>
                        <l>Yet pardon what amiſs they do,</l>
                        <l>Ev'n in this World unpuniſh'd too.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>From ills that rage, or ſeem to ſleep,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſervant keep:</l>
                        <l>As to this crime my hands are white;</l>
                        <l>My heart upright.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:121"/>
                        <l>Plead thou my cauſe, juſt Iudge defend me,</l>
                        <l>And joy in thy ſalvation ſend me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE IIII. <hi>Vpon the inſolency of the Tumults.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TO thee I fly thou ſole defence</l>
                        <l>Of my invaded innocence:</l>
                        <l>Who onely canſt the ſtubborn Main,</l>
                        <l>And people more enrag'd reſtrain.</l>
                        <l>The floods, the floods, or'e-ſwell their bounds,</l>
                        <l>Danger my threatned ſoul ſurrounds.</l>
                        <l>Mine and my Realms iniquity,</l>
                        <l>(The tumults of our ſouls gainſt thee)</l>
                        <l>Theſe popular inundations cauſe,</l>
                        <l>That bear down Loyalty and Lawes.</l>
                        <l>But thou to Seas didſt fix a ſhore,</l>
                        <l>And from the Deluge, Earth reſtore,</l>
                        <l>O quell theſe ſalvage Beaſts, and me</l>
                        <l>From their tumultuous Rapines free.</l>
                        <l>In all our Councells once again,</l>
                        <l>Let peace and equall freedome raign:</l>
                        <l>That Reaſon, and Religion may</l>
                        <l>Our Hearts, as Men and Chriſtians, ſway.</l>
                        <l>And we thy ſacred name ſhall bleſſe,</l>
                        <l>Who canſt, what men deſign, repreſſe.</l>
                        <l>Inſtruct their Leaders to repent,</l>
                        <l>Be Shame, not Death, their puniſhment:</l>
                        <l>Errours with Truth, Paſsion with Reaſon,</l>
                        <l>Schiſms with Love, with Laws bound Treaſon:</l>
                        <l>That like thy City, We in one</l>
                        <l>May meet. This grant for thy dear Son.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:122"/>
                     <head>ODE V. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties paſsing the Bill for Trien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Parliaments.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TO thee, my God, I ſtill appeal,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe all diſcerning eyes reveal,</l>
                        <l>The clouds that humane thoughts conceal.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A heart thou gav'ſt me to beſtow</l>
                        <l>Much on my Subjects, which muſt now</l>
                        <l>Learn much from them to undergo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy will be done, and ours deny'd,</l>
                        <l>When moſt to thine, it ſeems ally'd</l>
                        <l>And theirs, who thee pretend their guid.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Inſtruct me wiſely to employ</l>
                        <l>The Croſſes, that my hopes deſtroy;</l>
                        <l>As the fullfillings of my joy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I rais'd my own feares, theirs t'abate,</l>
                        <l>Unſetled mine, to fix their State,</l>
                        <l>Who recompence my love with hate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In this darke Storme my Pilot be,</l>
                        <l>Which to make home, nor ſuffers me,</l>
                        <l>Nor elſewere, with ſecurity.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My life thou ſafely canſt diſpoſe,</l>
                        <l>Circled by friends, or toſs'd by thoſe</l>
                        <l>Who poyſon what my love beſtowes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:122"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My bounty they, I thine abuſe:</l>
                        <l>Such Grace, ſuch Penitence infuſe,</l>
                        <l>We may not injure, thou accuſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>May I their errours rightly ſee,</l>
                        <l>By their ingratitude to me,</l>
                        <l>Wiſely reforming mine to thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That though from temporall bleſsings thrown,</l>
                        <l>By ſinns of others for my own;</l>
                        <l>Thy mercies may my ſufferings crown.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE VI. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties retirement from</hi> Weſtminſter.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OUR native freedome, Lord, preſerve,</l>
                        <l>Which bids our wills thy will obey:</l>
                        <l>Yet from our Conſcience never ſwerve,</l>
                        <l>Whil'ſt mens Decrees with Law we weigh,</l>
                        <l>And Reaſon, nor of ought allow</l>
                        <l>But that, to which our judgements bow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Where fix'd by thee I did reſide,</l>
                        <l>That place, by Subjects forc'd, I quitted:</l>
                        <l>Yet for their good my ſelf deny'd</l>
                        <l>In all to my diſpoſe ſubmitted:</l>
                        <l>Let no Demands in Tumults preſt,</l>
                        <l>From my conſent unjuſt pow'r wreſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The greateſt mischeif of my Foes,</l>
                        <l>Teach me with joy to entertain;</l>
                        <l>Ere the leaſt ſin that they propoſe,</l>
                        <l>The whiteneſs of my Conſcience ſtain:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:123"/>
                        <l>Iuſt freedome let thy People have,</l>
                        <l>Yet not my Soul be made a Slave.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou haſt diſpos'd me to a Throne,</l>
                        <l>And with a Crown my Temples deckt:</l>
                        <l>The reaſon which from thee I owne,</l>
                        <l>Let others Paſsions not ſubject.</l>
                        <l>So ſhall my truth with thee comply,</l>
                        <l>Though them I cannot ſatisfie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Whilſt I, by their injurious wrath,</l>
                        <l>With violence am forc'd away;</l>
                        <l>Guide thou my ſteps, nor from the path</l>
                        <l>Of Truth and Juſtice, let me ſtray.</l>
                        <l>For which my troubles now increaſe,</l>
                        <l>But they at laſt ſhall crown my Peace.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE VII. <hi>Vpon the Queens departure and abſence out of</hi> England.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOrd thoſe whom thou in Vowes haſt ty'd,</l>
                        <l>Yet now by diſtance doſt divide,</l>
                        <l>Here or in Heav'n unite.</l>
                        <l>Defend Us from deſpightfull Foes,</l>
                        <l>And by the ſufferings they impoſe,</l>
                        <l>Prepare Us for thy ſight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though in Religion we diſſent,</l>
                        <l>Hear our Devotions jointly bent</l>
                        <l>Thy ſacred Truth to finde.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:123"/>
                        <l>Love in our equall hearts infuſe</l>
                        <l>Of thee, and him, who us to excuſe</l>
                        <l>His ſinleſs life reſign'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With judgement and deſire endue,</l>
                        <l>Goodneſs to know and to purſue;</l>
                        <l>Theſe in our Souls prevent:</l>
                        <l>Ere Diſobedience Harbour win,</l>
                        <l>Or Blindneſs, be not that our ſin;</l>
                        <l>Nor this our puniſhment,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O let no Truth my Foes profeſs,</l>
                        <l>Be blemiſh'd by the wickedneſs</l>
                        <l>That in their actions thrives;</l>
                        <l>May Mine and others Conſtancy,</l>
                        <l>An Antidote more pow'rfull be</l>
                        <l>Againſt their poys' nous lives.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let that ſole Faith thou do'ſt approve,</l>
                        <l>In Loyall Peace, and humble Love,</l>
                        <l>(Their native dreſſe) appear:</l>
                        <l>Not in the loathſome black diſguiſe,</l>
                        <l>Of new Rebellious Hereſies,</l>
                        <l>Which they would force her weare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That ſhe whom Vowes make part of me,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſacred ſaving Truth may ſee,</l>
                        <l>From humane Droſſe refin'd;</l>
                        <l>And (in that Chriſtall Glaſs diſplay'd)</l>
                        <l>The mercies in his Blood convey'd,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe life his Precepts ſign'd;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:124"/>
                        <l>May knowledge of Earths vain delights,</l>
                        <l>Ecclips'd by unexpected Nights,</l>
                        <l>By ſudden Stormes ore-caſt;</l>
                        <l>Enflame our Spirits with deſire,</l>
                        <l>To thoſe Celeſtiall joyes t'aſpire,</l>
                        <l>Which time ſhall never waſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE VIII. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties repulſe at</hi> Hull, <hi>and the Fates of the</hi> Hothams.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHO vengeance on my wrongs haſt ſhowne,</l>
                        <l>And by my Foes, my Foes ore thrown:</l>
                        <l>Let not his fall invite</l>
                        <l>My Soul by cloſe delight;</l>
                        <l>To make thy juſt revenge her own.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou haſt reverted on his head</l>
                        <l>The miſchiefs he for others ſpread,</l>
                        <l>Unwiſh'd, unask'd by me:</l>
                        <l>That all the Earth may ſee;</l>
                        <l>Thou did'ſt my Cauſe in judgement plead.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I will not, dare not imprecate</l>
                        <l>The like on all that bear me hate.</l>
                        <l>No: to their Souls diſpence</l>
                        <l>Pardon and Penitence,</l>
                        <l>Charg'd wth no due afflictions weight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Deprive me not of Theams ſo fit</l>
                        <l>For Mercy: but their ſinns remit</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:124"/>
                        <l>Whoſe bold Demerit climbs,</l>
                        <l>Next thoſe ungratefull Crimes,</l>
                        <l>Of which thou Me art pleas'd t'acquit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Their Sinns be to their Conſcience preſt,</l>
                        <l>In Sorrow not in Iudgement dreſt;</l>
                        <l>The Thunder that was thrown</l>
                        <l>So dreadfully at one,</l>
                        <l>Be a juſt terror to the reſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Fear with repentant Knowledge joyn,</l>
                        <l>Of their malitious black Deſigne:</l>
                        <l>That to thy mercies they,</l>
                        <l>Finding the ſpacious way;</l>
                        <l>May thy devouring Wrath decline.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord, ſend thy Truth and Mercy down,</l>
                        <l>In them ſet faſt thy ſervants Throne,</l>
                        <l>Let Peace and Iuſtice meet,</l>
                        <l>With mutuall Kiſſes greet,</l>
                        <l>And prop my never fading Crown.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Be to our pray'r for Foes intent;</l>
                        <l>Whom (when thy foes) thou didſt prevent</l>
                        <l>With offer'd Clemency,</l>
                        <l>Sending thy Son to dye</l>
                        <l>For them who on his Death were bent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:125"/>
                     <head>ODE IX. <hi>Vpon the Liſting and Raiſing Armies againſt the King.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THrough humane clouds thy Raies</l>
                        <l>like Lightning glide;</l>
                        <l>No prejudice thy Sentence ſwaies,</l>
                        <l>For Knowledge is thy Iudgements guide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The proud, my Soul oppoſe,</l>
                        <l>And ſlight thy Lawes;</l>
                        <l>Help, Lord, for many are my Foes,</l>
                        <l>They hate me yet without a cauſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I never did (thou know'ſt)</l>
                        <l>Theſe Broiles begin,</l>
                        <l>In which, though I adventure moſt,</l>
                        <l>Yet I am certain leaſt to winn.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But oft deplor'd and ſtrove,</l>
                        <l>With care t'avoid;</l>
                        <l>My life ſuch dangers could not love,</l>
                        <l>Better to ſave than kill imploy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My other ſufferings far</l>
                        <l>Their Calumnie</l>
                        <l>Outweighs: who tell the World this war</l>
                        <l>(My greateſt croſs) was rais'd by Me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet this by ſilence I</l>
                        <l>Willingly could own;</l>
                        <l>Might it their malice ſatisfie,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt thou my innocence haſt known.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:125"/>
                        <l>Deceitfull Murtherers ſhall</l>
                        <l>Thy Vengeance finde;</l>
                        <l>Already ſome by timeleſs fall,</l>
                        <l>Are barr'd the fruit their Rage deſign'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who War affect ſuppreſs,</l>
                        <l>My God ariſe,</l>
                        <l>Lift up thy ſelf, my Foes increaſe,</l>
                        <l>Pregnant with Miſchief, Sin, and Lies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Life and Conſcience they</l>
                        <l>At once invade;</l>
                        <l>Let that to their fierce Rage a Prey,</l>
                        <l>Ere this to thy juſt Wrath be made.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My clearneſs Refuge claims;</l>
                        <l>Yet if my Blood</l>
                        <l>Can onely quench my Kingdoms flames,</l>
                        <l>Let my own Subjects ſluce the Flood.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But (O) the Blood of Me</l>
                        <l>their ſinfull King,</l>
                        <l>Waſht in my guiltleſs Saviours, be</l>
                        <l>Thy mercies unexhauſted Spring.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When Death, thy Wrath t'appeaſe</l>
                        <l>I undergo,</l>
                        <l>My People from this ſinn releaſe;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Forgive! They know not what they do.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:126"/>
                     <head>ODE X. <hi>Vpon the ſeizing the Kings Magazins, Forts Navy, and Militia.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O my God, to thee I fly,</l>
                        <l>Stronger than the Enemy;</l>
                        <l>Heaven nor Earth are wiſh'd by me,</l>
                        <l>In compariſon of thee.</l>
                        <l>Let me be when All deny'd,</l>
                        <l>More than All by thee ſupply'd.</l>
                        <l>Haſt to help, thou failſt not thoſe</l>
                        <l>Who their truſt in thee repoſe.</l>
                        <l>Rob'd of Pow'r to check their Will,</l>
                        <l>Who are blindly led to Kill,</l>
                        <l>By pretences to Protect;</l>
                        <l>I to thee my Eyes erect.</l>
                        <l>Help thou need'ſt not, nor ſhall I,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt thou doſt not thine deny;</l>
                        <l>To ſubdue or undergo.</l>
                        <l>If Succeſſe thou not beſtow,</l>
                        <l>Nor my ſafety wilt allow,</l>
                        <l>To thy judgement ſee I bow;</l>
                        <l>Which upon thy Children fall:</l>
                        <l>Nothing I, ſo thou be all.</l>
                        <l>Kings are unſecure that boaſt</l>
                        <l>In the number of an Hoaſt;</l>
                        <l>But thy numerous Mercies are</l>
                        <l>Our defence, O God of War.</l>
                        <l>Dangers on each ſide preſs neer;</l>
                        <l>Help; and Man I ſhall not fear.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:126"/>
                        <l>My diſtreſſes glory I</l>
                        <l>To thy juſtice will apply,</l>
                        <l>Glorify'd thy Mercy be,</l>
                        <l>In my ſafe delivery.</l>
                        <l>By my ſinns 'gainſt thee I fought,</l>
                        <l>And to robb thy Glory ſought;</l>
                        <l>Though thy Subject; by my own,</l>
                        <l>Juſtly me thou migh'ſt unthrone.</l>
                        <l>But break forth! nor let the Foe</l>
                        <l>Boaſt his God no ſtrength can ſhow.</l>
                        <l>In thy paths my footſteps guide,</l>
                        <l>Suffer not my feet to ſlide;</l>
                        <l>As thine Eye my Soul defend,</l>
                        <l>And thy ſhady wing extend,</l>
                        <l>From the wicked that oppoſe,</l>
                        <l>And with Malice me incloſe;</l>
                        <l>To thoſe joyes my conduct be,</l>
                        <l>Which in fullneſs wait on thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XI. <hi>Vpon the Nineteen Propoſitions ſent to the King.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>ETernall wiſedom armd with might,</l>
                        <l>With Truth and Right my Reaſon clear;</l>
                        <l>To which ſo make my will adhere,</l>
                        <l>No threats may from their Dictates fright:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou did'ſt not raiſe me to a Throne,</l>
                        <l>To barre me common liberty.</l>
                        <l>Shall that be nam'd a crime in me,</l>
                        <l>Which others as a vertue owne?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:127"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Unjuſtly they their King deny</l>
                        <l>The freedom, which all mortalls claim:</l>
                        <l>Whilſt ev'n themſelves exact the ſame,</l>
                        <l>With partiall pertinacity.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To thee I pray who through the maze</l>
                        <l>Of my own thoughts, and ſuits (like ſnares</l>
                        <l>Spread to involve my ſoul in cares)</l>
                        <l>Canſt ſurely guide: make plain thy waies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let not my Paſsions cloud thy light;</l>
                        <l>Thy Word my Rule, thy Praiſe my End.</l>
                        <l>To all I cannot, will not bend</l>
                        <l>To ſome; Thee pleas'd all elſe I ſlight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who Plots unweav'ſt, and the Self-wiſe</l>
                        <l>Entangl'ſt in their own deſigne;</l>
                        <l>To thy wiſe Truth my ſoul incline,</l>
                        <l>And mens eſteeme I ſhall deſpiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The leſſe my wiſedom ſhall appear,</l>
                        <l>More thine that guide'ſt me ſhines; whilſt I</l>
                        <l>Nothing through willfullneſs deny,</l>
                        <l>Nor grant through Flattery, or Fear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No ſuits by my conſent be ſign'd,</l>
                        <l>Injurious to the publike good:</l>
                        <l>No publike benefits withſtood,</l>
                        <l>To ſooth my own diſſenting mind.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:127"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To ſuch, though from my Enemies,</l>
                        <l>Teach me to give a free acceſſe;</l>
                        <l>Our honeſt errours thou canſt bleſſe,</l>
                        <l>As blaſt the Counſells falſely wiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Since private words thy ſcourge obey,</l>
                        <l>Teach me to poiſe what I declare.</l>
                        <l>The bolder mens Petitions are,</l>
                        <l>Let me the more my Anſwers weigh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though troubles Me and mine attend,</l>
                        <l>And Peace our Preſſures would acquit;</l>
                        <l>Yet let me not to purchaſe it,</l>
                        <l>My Conſcience (which is thine) expend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XII. <hi>Vpon the Rebellion and troubles in</hi> Ireland.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THy mercies Lord (hence in diſpleaſure fled)</l>
                        <l>On me and my torn Kingdoms I implore:</l>
                        <l>Whoſe loſs we both too juſty merited,</l>
                        <l>But never can deſerve thou ſhouldſt reſtore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou ſeeſt the cruelty that Chriſtians uſe,</l>
                        <l>In the falſe colours of Religion dy'd;</l>
                        <l>As if the names of Chriſtians they ſhould loſe,</l>
                        <l>Unleſs they one another crucify'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Since we thy Truth and Charity deſpis'd,</l>
                        <l>Errour, and Hatred now their room poſſeſs.</l>
                        <l>My God, O pardon thoſe thou haſt chaſtiz'd;</l>
                        <l>Our wounds with penitentiall Balm redreſs</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:128"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Make not our ſufferings leſs in thy eſteem;</l>
                        <l>And to our Conſcience let our ſins appear,</l>
                        <l>As they in th'mirrour of thy judgements ſeem;</l>
                        <l>Which to ſmall crimes are never ſo ſevere.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Remove their numerous weight, and be appeas'd,</l>
                        <l>Yet then our ſinns may they afflict us leſs:</l>
                        <l>More willing to repent than to be eas'd,</l>
                        <l>With peace our Souls, &amp; next our Kingdoms bleſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By thy great mercy our offences drown'd,</l>
                        <l>In the calme Sea of our Redeemers blood:</l>
                        <l>And through the purple current of our own,</l>
                        <l>Steer us at laſt to Plenty, Peace, and Good.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To me a ſhare of all the ills that preſs</l>
                        <l>My Subjects, doth my wide relation bring:</l>
                        <l>Give me a pious ſenſe of their diſtreſs,</l>
                        <l>Such as befits their Father and their King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let the reproachfull breath their Malice ſpreads,</l>
                        <l>Kindle in me compaſsionate deſires:</l>
                        <l>My Charity heap Coles upon their heads,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe zealous cruelty my Kingdom fires.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O reſcue thoſe whom yet thou haſt preſerv'd,</l>
                        <l>Reduceing all to thy Truths ſaving waies;</l>
                        <l>Who by miſtake or ignorance have ſwerv'd,</l>
                        <l>But puniſh them who theſe combuſtions raiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Not with the guilty thou the innocent,</l>
                        <l>Nor th'erring, wilt with the malitious ſlay:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:128"/>
                        <l>To Foes, through avarice on Slaughter bent,</l>
                        <l>Give not that poor ſeduced Realm away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In the devouring Fornace of thine ire,</l>
                        <l>A race, that may thy mercy praiſe, maintain.</l>
                        <l>Deal not with me as mens untruths require,</l>
                        <l>But as my guiltleſs hands are free from ſtain.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If I have ſought or lov'd my Kingdomes woes,</l>
                        <l>Nor did my ſtudies faithfully employ,</l>
                        <l>Theſe bloody wild diſtractions to compoſe,</l>
                        <l>Then let thy hand my fathers houſe deſtroy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That I have Foes enough thou Lord doeſt ſee,</l>
                        <l>I durſt not call thy curſe on me and mine,</l>
                        <l>Were I not guiltleſs to my ſelf and thee;</l>
                        <l>Thy mercies are my truſt: Thy wrath decline.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XIII. <hi>Vpon the calling in of the Scots.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MY troubles, Lord, are multipli'd,</l>
                        <l>O ſuccour the diſtreſt!</l>
                        <l>In ſimpleſt truth thy Servant guide,</l>
                        <l>The wiſeſt intereſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>From th'aſſociate ſtrength of Foes</l>
                        <l>Be thou my juſt defence,</l>
                        <l>Who, for the Serpents craft, depoſe</l>
                        <l>The Doves white Innocence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:129"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though to oppreſſe Me they agree;</l>
                        <l>Combin'd in mutuall aid,</l>
                        <l>Let not my Soul and Honours, be</l>
                        <l>to their deceits betray'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Devotion, and Allegiance, thou</l>
                        <l>Canſt in their hearts renue;</l>
                        <l>That him they may reſtore, whom now</l>
                        <l>They eagerly purſue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Love of thy Truth preſerve in me,</l>
                        <l>And I deſpair not theirs:</l>
                        <l>At thy command the flowing Sea</l>
                        <l>Back to its Bound repair's.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My God, on thee my hopes depend,</l>
                        <l>Me let not ſhame ſurprize,</l>
                        <l>But them who without cauſe offend;</l>
                        <l>Repulſe my Enemies.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Armour be Integrity,</l>
                        <l>For Lord, on thee I wait:</l>
                        <l>The Church, which thou haſt own'd, ſet free</l>
                        <l>From her perplex'd eſtate.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XIV. <hi>Vpon the Covenant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOrd, I to thee direct my cries,</l>
                        <l>My Subjects forward Oaths remit:</l>
                        <l>Quicken their ſenſe of thoſe firm ties,</l>
                        <l>By law upon their Conſcience knit.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:129"/>
                        <l>With which no pious, no pretence</l>
                        <l>Of Reformation can diſpence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Religion owns no injury:</l>
                        <l>No Sacreledge by thee allow'd;</l>
                        <l>Though mask'd with hate t'Idolatry:</l>
                        <l>Their zeal-diſguiſed fraud uncloud.</l>
                        <l>Things Holy tis a ſnare to take,</l>
                        <l>And after Vowes enquiry make.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aſſsiſt thy ſervant to withſtand</l>
                        <l>Rapines involv'd in Perjury:</l>
                        <l>Nor ever let me wear the brand</l>
                        <l>Of having rob'd thy Church and thee.</l>
                        <l>Since what to us thy bounty gives,</l>
                        <l>From us thy Clemency receives.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though my Revenues are decreaſt,</l>
                        <l>My debts enlarg'd, my Treaſures drain'd,</l>
                        <l>Let not my wants, by ſuch unbleſt</l>
                        <l>Rapines, conſent to be ſuſtain'd:</l>
                        <l>Leaſt from thy Altar fall a Cole,</l>
                        <l>And fire at once my Throne and Soul.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let no vain publike Indigence,</l>
                        <l>The Church from her endowments ſever,</l>
                        <l>The 'State, by peacefull Providence,</l>
                        <l>May theirs regain the Church can never:</l>
                        <l>Whilſt Charity is thought a vice,</l>
                        <l>Religion plac'd in Avarice.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:130"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let them who in thy Temple ſerve,</l>
                        <l>What pious Donors gave, enjoy:</l>
                        <l>And (thoſe incitements to deſerve)</l>
                        <l>Their wealth, to aid the low, imploy</l>
                        <l>The Prieſts in Righteouſneſs array'd,</l>
                        <l>The hunger of the Poor allai'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No hallow'd things let Swine divide,</l>
                        <l>Nor Doggs devour the Churches bread:</l>
                        <l>But Grin and Snarle unſatisfi'd.</l>
                        <l>Whilſt all that have already fed</l>
                        <l>Death in thoſe ſacred morſells finde,</l>
                        <l>And leave a rotten name behinde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord, break the Treaſons of my Foes,</l>
                        <l>In Sacriledge Confederate:</l>
                        <l>Diſjoin the Hearts and Tongues of thoſe</l>
                        <l>Who bandy 'gainſt the Church and State.</l>
                        <l>Let all the world their folly ſee,</l>
                        <l>And in my clearneſs ſuccour me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XV. <hi>Vpon the Jealouſies raiſed, and Scandalls caſt upon the King</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O Lord thou ſeeſt my wrongs abound;</l>
                        <l>Lyons enrag'd my Soul ſurround,</l>
                        <l>With poi snous words</l>
                        <l>Their Tongues like Swords,</l>
                        <l>Their teeth like Arrows wound.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:130"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My foes reproach me all the day,</l>
                        <l>And ſworn deceits together lay;</l>
                        <l>My God! how long</l>
                        <l>Shall they grow ſtrong,</l>
                        <l>Who with vain Lies inveigh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Calumnies which they have ſown</l>
                        <l>On every ſide to thee are known,</l>
                        <l>Hold not thy peace</l>
                        <l>Leaſt they increaſe,</l>
                        <l>And bury my Renown.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Lier thou wilt ruinate,</l>
                        <l>The Bloody and the falſe do'ſt hate;</l>
                        <l>Let my upright</l>
                        <l>Intents, a light,</l>
                        <l>Clear as the Sun dilate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My patience let not wrath out-weigh,</l>
                        <l>Nor ſilence Innocence betray,</l>
                        <l>That I may tread,</l>
                        <l>As thou haſt led,</l>
                        <l>Curſes with bleſsings pay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shimei,</hi> when his envenom'd pride</l>
                        <l>Seem'd by thy judgements juſtifi'd,</l>
                        <l>Thou didſt ore-throw:</l>
                        <l>But deal not ſo</l>
                        <l>With them that me deride.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Pray'r and Patience in theſe wrongs,</l>
                        <l>Like water, cool, and quench their toungs;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:131"/>
                        <l>Enflam'd with Ire,</l>
                        <l>By that black fire</l>
                        <l>Which unto Hell belongs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O let my Deeds their Words refute,</l>
                        <l>Nor they enjoy the deadly fruit</l>
                        <l>Which (dip'd in gall)</l>
                        <l>Their lipps let fall:</l>
                        <l>But my indulgent ſuit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Soul to meek Devotion win:</l>
                        <l>That I thy boundleſſe mercies, in</l>
                        <l>Their malice, may</l>
                        <l>With joy ſurvay;</l>
                        <l>Thy juſtice in their ſin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O let the Curſes they have thrown</l>
                        <l>At me, invite thy bleſsings down.</l>
                        <l>What ſome refuſe,</l>
                        <l>Be pleas'd to chuſe</l>
                        <l>For the Head corner ſtone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Look down from thy eternall Tower,</l>
                        <l>Redeem from them that would devoure:</l>
                        <l>My Soul O hide,</l>
                        <l>From mens bold pride,</l>
                        <l>From their invective power.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:131"/>
                     <head>ODE XVI. <hi>Vpon the Ordinance againſt the Common-prayer-book.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou ſtill the ſame for ever bleſt,</l>
                        <l>Whom mercies infinite inveſt,</l>
                        <l>In various conſtancy expreſt?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou haſt us with new ſenſe indu'd</l>
                        <l>Of our old wants, nor ſcornſt renew'd</l>
                        <l>Deſires, in unchang'd words purſu'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Still let our fix'd Devotions joyne;</l>
                        <l>Our ſuits to thy firm will encline;</l>
                        <l>Our fervent Spirits move by thine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For thou, in all perfection wiſe,</l>
                        <l>Nor novelty in prayer doſt prize,</l>
                        <l>Nor pious conſtancy deſpiſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By thy command preferring neither,</l>
                        <l>Left in thy Churches pow r together,</l>
                        <l>To uſe, but not diſparage either.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Devotions moderately guide,</l>
                        <l>None in jur'd, none juſt helps deny'd,</l>
                        <l>By others ignorance or pride.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Since Errours ever are unſure,</l>
                        <l>And by pretence of change allure;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt truth in Union is ſecure:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:132"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Preſerve thy Church, that no unfit</l>
                        <l>Orders (as various) ſhe admit;</l>
                        <l>Nor Conſtancy, as formall, quit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord, chaſe Hypocriſie away,</l>
                        <l>And then (we know) we ſafely may,</l>
                        <l>In ſetled forms, or praiſe, or pray.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Teach us what dwells within to mend,</l>
                        <l>And leſſe we outwards need attend.</l>
                        <l>From bold blind zeal thy Church defend.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XVII. <hi>Vpon the differences between the King, and the two Houſes, in point of Church-Government.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TO thee my uprightneſs is known,</l>
                        <l>Who haſt appointed me to own</l>
                        <l>Thy ſacred Faiths defence;</l>
                        <l>O let me not of thee forlorn,</l>
                        <l>Againſt my Conſcience be ore-born,</l>
                        <l>By floods of violence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Up Lord, in thine own cauſe ariſe;</l>
                        <l>Leaſt Schiſm make thy Church its prize,</l>
                        <l>And trample on her pow'r;</l>
                        <l>From thee continued to our time,</l>
                        <l>When Wealth is made her fatall crime;</l>
                        <l>Her ſin is her fair Dow'r.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:132"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Whom, ſome have plunderd, others wound,</l>
                        <l>The reſt deſerted as they found,</l>
                        <l>Or in her ſufferings joy:</l>
                        <l>May I her hurts, and wants relieve,</l>
                        <l>The power which I from thee receive:</l>
                        <l>Teach me for thee t imploy,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To her that love be ſtill ſuſtain'd,</l>
                        <l>I owe as Chriſtian, though reſtrain'd:</l>
                        <l>As King from all my right;</l>
                        <l>The bounties on thy Church diſplaid:</l>
                        <l>By providence, let none invade,</l>
                        <l>With ſacrilegious might.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Forgive their Errour, and their Sin,</l>
                        <l>Who wrought thy ſufferance to let in:</l>
                        <l>Flie Foxes and wild Boars,</l>
                        <l>To lay that goodly Vineyard waſt,</l>
                        <l>Which thy right hand in planting grac'd</l>
                        <l>Watred with heavenly ſhowers.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Oh! never let ſuch Infamy,</l>
                        <l>Brand my clear Name, as to agree:</l>
                        <l>T'oppoſe the Church and thoſe,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe Errours I ſhould rather hide:</l>
                        <l>With ſilence, or with meekneſs chide,</l>
                        <l>Than to contempt expoſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The wrongs which with thy Church I bear,</l>
                        <l>And for her ſake, to thee appear:</l>
                        <l>Haſt, Lord, to ſet us free,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:133"/>
                        <l>From ravenous men of reaſon void:</l>
                        <l>Who have old Bounds of Peace deſtroi'd,</l>
                        <l>To let in Hereſie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou God of Peace and Order, quell</l>
                        <l>The malice of our Foes, diſpell</l>
                        <l>Their black devices, then</l>
                        <l>May we, who in thy Church delight,</l>
                        <l>The wonders of thy Prayſe recite,</l>
                        <l>Before the Sons of men.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XVIII. <hi>Vpon the</hi> Uxbridge <hi>Treatie,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OF Peace and Reaſon Lord!</l>
                        <l>Delighting in accord;</l>
                        <l>The wicked who from ſin,</l>
                        <l>With offer'd Grace would win!</l>
                        <l>Whoſe mercy courts to ſave,</l>
                        <l>Though power to kill thou have!</l>
                        <l>(Our hearts to ſoftneſs woo'd</l>
                        <l>In our Redeemers blood)</l>
                        <l>Perſwade us to agree,</l>
                        <l>Both with our ſelves and thee:</l>
                        <l>As Men and Chriſtians ought,</l>
                        <l>Peace often have I ſought,</l>
                        <l>But it no ſooner name,</l>
                        <l>Than war my Foes proclaim.</l>
                        <l>Our actions never may,</l>
                        <l>Deſtructive Paſſions ſway.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:133"/>
                        <l>Our Judgments clear, that we</l>
                        <l>Thy Truth may plainly ſee.</l>
                        <l>Our ſtubborn Hearts incline,</l>
                        <l>In bonds of Peace to joyne.</l>
                        <l>Our irreligious hate</l>
                        <l>To thee, oh diſſipate;</l>
                        <l>That to our ſelves, remove</l>
                        <l>With interchanged Love,</l>
                        <l>The war our ſins have wrought,</l>
                        <l>With Peace, which Chriſt hath bought;</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XIX. <hi>Vpon the various events of War, Victories, and Defeats.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With ready joy oh let me, Lord! agree</l>
                        <l>To be orecome when thou wilt have it ſo:</l>
                        <l>Inſtruct me in the nobleſt Victory,</l>
                        <l>By patience to ſubdue my ſelf, and foe;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Conqueſt like Chriſts, a Chriſtian King beſt ſhew:</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mold us to Piety betwixt thy Hands,</l>
                        <l>Preſt by thy left, ſupported by thy right;</l>
                        <l>Pardon the pride of our ſuccesfull Bands,</l>
                        <l>And the repinings of our luckleſs Fight,</l>
                        <l>When (truſting in our own) deny'd thy might:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When we are ought, or nothing, be thou All;</l>
                        <l>That thy wide glory's the whole World may fill,</l>
                        <l>Or in our Conqueſt, or inglorious fall.</l>
                        <l>Thou know'ſt with what Regret I ſuffer ill,</l>
                        <l>From thoſe whoſe Good's the ſcope of all my will.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:134"/>
                        <l>The Ills they force me to inflict, I bear;</l>
                        <l>And in their puniſhments, my own embrace,</l>
                        <l>Victor or vanquiſh'd? ſince a double ſhare</l>
                        <l>Of certain ſuffering doth my Hope diſplace,</l>
                        <l>Grant me a double Portion of thy Grace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As moſt afflicted, Lord reform me moſt,</l>
                        <l>To ſee our Peace, and to reſtore it bleſt.</l>
                        <l>That all ſubdu'd by reaſons power, may boaſt,</l>
                        <l>A mutuall Conqueſt, common ſtrife ſuppreſt</l>
                        <l>In publick Union, our joynt Intereſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But if as ſins of Peace provok'd this War,</l>
                        <l>Peace for the ſins of War thou ſhouldſt deny,</l>
                        <l>Making our miſeries more circular:</l>
                        <l>Yet let thy ſervant midſt theſe broyles enjoy</l>
                        <l>That Peace the World nor gives, nor can deſtroy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To me impute not, Lord! the purple Flood,</l>
                        <l>Shed with unwilling grief in my defence.</l>
                        <l>But waſh me in my Saviours precious blood:</l>
                        <l>By whom my troubles hope a quick diſpence;</l>
                        <l>For ſhort are impious joy's, and Confidence.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XX. <hi>Vpon the Reformation of the Times.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOrd, thou who Beauty canſt return,</l>
                        <l>To them that mourn;</l>
                        <l>And the diſguis'd pretext of Art,</l>
                        <l>To Truth convert;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:134"/>
                        <l>Oh let us not by ſhews be guil'd,</l>
                        <l>Seem pure without, within defil'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Within, where moſt deform'd we are,</l>
                        <l>Be our firſt care,</l>
                        <l>Then with clear eyes the Church we may</l>
                        <l>And State ſurvey.</l>
                        <l>Our Hearts, our Spirits, Lord, renew,</l>
                        <l>That we thy Dictates may purſue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Upon our foul diſorders, bred</l>
                        <l>By them, who (led</l>
                        <l>With rage) to purge us undertook,</l>
                        <l>With pity look.</l>
                        <l>Quench thou the fire that Factions raiſe,</l>
                        <l>From Reformations ſpecious Blaze.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As their Diviſion, Lord, proclaims</l>
                        <l>Their weak, bad Aims?</l>
                        <l>So let us (in thoſe fires refin'd)</l>
                        <l>In love be joyn'd;</l>
                        <l>From Paſſions freed: bleſt with increaſe</l>
                        <l>Of inward Vertue, outward Peace.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XXI. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties Letters taken and divulg'd?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou Lord, who by thy wiſe Decree,</l>
                        <l>Do'ſt our Contingency diſpoſe;</l>
                        <l>Make me thy conſtant mercyes ſee,</l>
                        <l>In the advantage of my Foes.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:135"/>
                        <l>Thou canſt their Councells turn away,</l>
                        <l>And their devices ruinate:</l>
                        <l>Who all my ſecrets open lay,</l>
                        <l>To work me in my Peoples hate.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To thy Omniſcience I repair,</l>
                        <l>Witneſs with my Integrity,</l>
                        <l>How falſe the wreſted Comments are,</l>
                        <l>Which they to what I write apply.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The ill directed by their Aim</l>
                        <l>To me; ſo turn upon their Head,</l>
                        <l>That they may be involv'd in ſhame;</l>
                        <l>And with Confuſion over ſpread.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou ſeeſt with what malicious Art,</l>
                        <l>They ſeek to cloud me with diſgrace:</l>
                        <l>But give me a ſubmiſſive Heart,</l>
                        <l>Diſhonour for thy ſake t'embrace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Make me intent to honour thee,</l>
                        <l>And I in Honour ſhall abound;</l>
                        <l>Reſtor'd to my firſt Dignity,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe with equal Patience crown'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou art in Majeſty array'd!</l>
                        <l>Goodnes and Glory from Thee ſpring:</l>
                        <l>With Wiſdome, Juſtice, Mercy aid,</l>
                        <l>I ſhall not want what fits a King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou the Exalter of my Head,</l>
                        <l>In Thee is my Salvation plac't:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:135"/>
                        <l>Lord by thy Grace to Glory lead,</l>
                        <l>Which to Eternitie ſhall laſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XXII. <hi>Vpon his Majeſties leaving</hi> Oxford, <hi>and going to the Scots.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou, who all Souls, all Conſciences doſt ſway,</l>
                        <l>To thee I look diſmay'd!</l>
                        <l>To thy Protection I commit my way.</l>
                        <l>Thou, who my life did'ſt aide,</l>
                        <l>Still in thy weakneſs canſt thy ſtrength diſplay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A fiery Pillar in dark nights to me,</l>
                        <l>And with thy light direct,</l>
                        <l>In ſcorching Day's a cloudy Pillar be;</l>
                        <l>And with thy ſhade protect.</l>
                        <l>O let me find both Sun, and Shield in Thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My life I was not by perverſeneſs wrought</l>
                        <l>To hazard thus t'xpoſe:</l>
                        <l>But Reaſon, Honour, and Religion taught,</l>
                        <l>To guard my ſelf from thoſe,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe impious force to wreſt them from me ſought.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let not the juſt Reſolves, I have endu'd</l>
                        <l>With outward ſtrength, abate</l>
                        <l>A Conſcience where no wrong did e're intrude:</l>
                        <l>Be my Aſſociate,</l>
                        <l>In my Deſertions greateſt Solitude.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:136"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Fort of Reaſon let me not betray,</l>
                        <l>Truſted to keep for Thee.</l>
                        <l>From thy Salvation that I never ſtray,</l>
                        <l>My conſtant Conduct be.</l>
                        <l>If Thee I pleaſe, Peace ſhall my Foes allay.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XXIII. <hi>Vpon the Scots delivering the King to the Engliſh, and his Captivity at</hi> Holmeby</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou that alone art infinite</l>
                        <l>In good, and greatneſs; dwel'ſt with me,</l>
                        <l>Weigh'd with thy Preſence Life is light,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſervice perfect Liberty:</l>
                        <l>Own me for thine, I cannot but be free.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>As I am Man with Reaſon bleſs,</l>
                        <l>With Zeal as Chriſtian; Right as King:</l>
                        <l>Of outwards ſtript, let me poſſeſs</l>
                        <l>Thee in the joy's that from Thee ſpring;</l>
                        <l>Which gainſt my will no force can from me wring.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let not my Paſſion over boyle</l>
                        <l>To fruitleſs Rage, or ſordid fear:</l>
                        <l>They think him helpleſs whom they foyle:</l>
                        <l>But let thy chearfull light appear,</l>
                        <l>And ſecure freedome ſhall my glories clear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Befitting my afflicted ſtate,</l>
                        <l>A patient Conſtancy beſtow:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:136"/>
                        <l>My ſtrength and hopes are diſsipate,</l>
                        <l>My ſelf impriſon'd by the Foe:</l>
                        <l>O be not far, leaſt they too mighty grow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Aſcorn and wonder I am made;</l>
                        <l>Thou my defence and ſuccour be:</l>
                        <l>My Foes aſham'd to ſee thy aid,</l>
                        <l>In thy free Spirit ſettle me</l>
                        <l>To act and ſuffer, what is will'd by Thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Soul into thy favour bring,</l>
                        <l>For She her Hope in Thee hath plac't?</l>
                        <l>My ſhelter is thy ſhady Wing,</l>
                        <l>Till theſe Calamities be paſt:</l>
                        <l>Riſe to deliver us, my God make haſt!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy mercy (though the Life it gives,</l>
                        <l>Thou take away) ſhall be my Truſt:</l>
                        <l>I know that my Redeemer lives,</l>
                        <l>Though in Deaths vale reſolv'd to Duſt,</l>
                        <l>Yet ſhall no taint of fear my bright Faith ruſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XXIIII. <hi>Vpon their denying his Majeſty the attendance of his Chaplains.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TO Thee my ſolitary Pray'rs I ſend,</l>
                        <l>The help that others my Diſtreſs deny,</l>
                        <l>With thy aſsiſtant Spirit Lord ſupply:</l>
                        <l>To dulneſs Life, Light to my Darkneſs lend.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:137"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou, Sun that beams of Righteouſnes doſt ſpread,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſacred Spring of heavenly Light and heat,</l>
                        <l>Both warmth and clearneſs in my Heart beget,</l>
                        <l>Inſtruct, and for thy Servant intercede.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Fulneſs, ſufficience, favour thee array;</l>
                        <l>Enough Thou Comfort art, and Company:</l>
                        <l>Thou art my King, my Prieſt and Prophet be;</l>
                        <l>Rule, teach, pray, in me, for me, with me ſtay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Jacob</hi> who ſingly did with Thee conteſt</l>
                        <l>In ſacred Duell, Thee his ſecond had:</l>
                        <l>He conquer'd, and a bleſſing (by thy aid)</l>
                        <l>From Thee with welcome Violence did wreſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With mercy on thy Servant be intent,</l>
                        <l>Who his Devotions once with them did joyne,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe fervour might inflame the cold of mine;</l>
                        <l>When to thy Houſe with Joy and Peace we went.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Of thoſe Occaſions our neglect forgive,</l>
                        <l>Which we with juſt Improvement would not ſcan;</l>
                        <l>Now like the deſert-hunting Pelican,</l>
                        <l>Or Sparrow pearch'd on ſome houſe-top I live.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And ſcatter'd like a dying Coale, from all</l>
                        <l>Thoſe pious glowings that might fire impart:</l>
                        <l>Keep and increaſe on th'Altar of my Heart,</l>
                        <l>On Thee in ſacrifice of Pray'r to call.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:137"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet thou that doſt not break the bruiſed Reed,</l>
                        <l>Nor quench the ſmoaking Flax, oh! not deſpiſe,</l>
                        <l>The ſmother'd Pray'rs that from my lone Soul riſe,</l>
                        <l>Deny'd the helps which I deſire and need.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The hardneſs of their Hearts, let ſoften mine;</l>
                        <l>Their hate my Love, denyall Prayrs excite,</l>
                        <l>Their deafneſs thy Attention Lord invite,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe ready Eare, Heart, Hand to help incline.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Men may debar thy Churches outward right,</l>
                        <l>Not inward Grace to humble minds convey'd.</l>
                        <l>O make me ſuch, and thou wilt Teach, Hear, Aid:</l>
                        <l>A broken contrite Heart, thou wilt not ſlight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou Temple, Altar, Sacrifice and Prieſt,</l>
                        <l>At once canſt make me; who each day alone</l>
                        <l>In Vowes Pray'rs, Tears am thy Oblation:</l>
                        <l>By whom prepar'd, accepted, and poſſeſt?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou didſt the Widow's Meale and Oyle encreaſe,</l>
                        <l>And ſecretly by ſtrange ſupply's infuſe</l>
                        <l>Into the Veſſel and unwaſting Cruze,</l>
                        <l>Which with the Drought and Dearth did only ceaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O my forſaken widow'd Soul preſerve,</l>
                        <l>Let not thy Truth and ſweet Effuſions fail</l>
                        <l>My memory and heart, but ſo prevail,</l>
                        <l>Kept from accuſtom'd food, I may not ſterve.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:138"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet better ſterve than by their Hands to feed,</l>
                        <l>Who mix my Bread with Aſhes, and infect</l>
                        <l>My Wine with Gall; who torture, not direct;</l>
                        <l>Prone to reproches, which their Pray'rs exceed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To my Deſtruction they pervert thy Word,</l>
                        <l>O be it not eternally to theirs:</l>
                        <l>Devouring under colour of long Pray'rs,</l>
                        <l>The Houſes of their Brethren, King, and Lord.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let not the Balme of theſe Men break my Head,</l>
                        <l>Nor let their Cordials my heart oppreſs:</l>
                        <l>Gainſt their preciſely colour'd wickedneſs,</l>
                        <l>My fervent Pray'rs inceſſantly ſhall plead.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord from the Snares their treacherous Lips include,</l>
                        <l>Their poy'snous toungs, &amp; from their words ſharp fire</l>
                        <l>Keep me and thoſe who my Souls good deſire,</l>
                        <l>Relieving with their Pray'rs my ſolitude.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="ode">
                     <head>ODE XXV. <hi>Penitentiall Meditations and Vowes in the Kings ſolitude at</hi> Homeby.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My God, my King incline thine Eare,</l>
                        <l>My cry to Thee directed hear.</l>
                        <l>Incens'd I ſaid, we from Thy Care</l>
                        <l>Are caſt: yet Thou receiv'ſt my Pray'r.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy Rigor who can fatisfie?</l>
                        <l>But to thy mercy's ſinners fly.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:138"/>
                        <l>Lord I acknowledg my offence,</l>
                        <l>Dilated in my Eminence.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The ſins I act, or do permit</l>
                        <l>By unimproved Pow'r acquit.</l>
                        <l>Rebellious I to Thee became,</l>
                        <l>Now, Priſoner to my Subjects am.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet though reſtrain'd my Perſon be,</l>
                        <l>By grace enlarge my Heart to Thee;</l>
                        <l>Though <hi>Davids</hi> Piety I want,</l>
                        <l>His griefs I have; His comforts grant!</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>O be my Penitentiall ſenſe</l>
                        <l>Of ſins, their Pardons evidence.</l>
                        <l>Eſteem not our Afflictions ſmall,</l>
                        <l>Though our loud Crimes for greater call</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Turn Thee, O Lord, Thy mercy ſhew,</l>
                        <l>For I am deſolate and Low.</l>
                        <l>The ſorrow's of my Heart increaſe,</l>
                        <l>O give my miſeries releaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Haſt Thou forgotten to be kind?</l>
                        <l>In wrath thy tender Care confin'd?</l>
                        <l>O call to mind thy Love of old,</l>
                        <l>And thy Compaſsions manifold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Amongſt the living I expected,</l>
                        <l>Thy Goodneſs, elſe had been dejected.</l>
                        <l>Let not our proſperour ſins make leſs,</l>
                        <l>The benefits of ous diſtreſs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:139"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Conſume the Droſs in this ſharp fire,</l>
                        <l>Which by long Peace, we did acquire:</l>
                        <l>On us if Thou Afflictions lay,</l>
                        <l>Take not thy ſtrengthining Grace away.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With patient Penitence ſupply</l>
                        <l>The want of our Proſperity.</l>
                        <l>And if thy Wrath not yet ſhall end,</l>
                        <l>If ſtill thy Juſtice thou extend:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Me and my Fathers Houſe ore-run,</l>
                        <l>As for theſe ſheep what have they done?</l>
                        <l>O let my ſufferings ſatiate thoſe,</l>
                        <l>Who to thy Church and me are Foes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But not when they moſt cruell grow,</l>
                        <l>My wider Charity out-goe:</l>
                        <l>No vengefull thought my Patience ſtain,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe glory's thine, but mine the gain.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Me thou to Pardon haſt inclin'd,</l>
                        <l>Let both our Foes thy Pardon find:</l>
                        <l>And now as Thou my heart doſt bow</l>
                        <l>To Pray'r, hear, and accept my vow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If thou remember us in Love,</l>
                        <l>Nor wilt thy ſacred Light remove;</l>
                        <l>Of Law and Juſtice repoſſeſt,</l>
                        <l>Faction and Hereſie ſuppreſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If me and mine thou wilt reſtore</l>
                        <l>To the juſt Rights we held before:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:139"/>
                        <l>If thou each ſubjects ſtubborn Heart</l>
                        <l>By Piety to Thee convert:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By humble Loyalty to Me,</l>
                        <l>And to themſelves by Charity;</l>
                        <l>From civil Broyles, if thou releaſe,</l>
                        <l>And mak'ſt their fatal cauſes ceaſe:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If thou free Councels wilt diſpence,</l>
                        <l>Not curb'd by vulgar inſolence:</l>
                        <l>If thou my Conſcience wilt defend:</l>
                        <l>Nor to Church Rapins let me bend:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If me with Power thou reinveſt,</l>
                        <l>Such as thy Glorys may atteſt,</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall my ſoul thy Prayſe proclaim:</l>
                        <l>And to thy people laud thy Name:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then ſhall thy truth, and thy Renown</l>
                        <l>My only treaſure be and Crown,</l>
                        <l>Then I with Equity ſhall ſway;</l>
                        <l>In Iuſtice ſhall my Realms obay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That as my Right from Thee alone,</l>
                        <l>I may my Reſtitution owne:</l>
                        <l>If I by thy Aſſiſtance come</l>
                        <l>With Honor, Peace, and ſafety home.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If thou once more the awfull ſword</l>
                        <l>To puniſh and protect afford,</l>
                        <l>Then all ſhall ſee my Foes partake,</l>
                        <l>This Vow which now to Thee I make.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:140"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What now as Chriſtian I forgive,</l>
                        <l>No ſnare of law ſhall back retrieve.</l>
                        <l>Me from my ſelf their Skill can part,</l>
                        <l>But I will never learn that art.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A full Indemnity ſhall clear</l>
                        <l>The growing doubts of jealous fear:</l>
                        <l>Strict Amneſty ſhall Peace prefer,</l>
                        <l>And in Oblivion wrongs interre.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No future Councells ſhall controle</l>
                        <l>This ſolemne purpoſe of my Soul:</l>
                        <l>To me let Mercy ſo increaſe,</l>
                        <l>As I reſolve on Truth and Peace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>To my Petition, Lord, attend,</l>
                        <l>Which Lips with guile untainted ſend:</l>
                        <l>His Name be bleſt who hears my Cry,</l>
                        <l>Nor his full mercy will deny.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Soul thy way to God commit,</l>
                        <l>Him truſt, and he ſhall perfect it.</l>
                        <l>If not reſtor'd, yet who am I,</l>
                        <l>That I ſhould charge thee fooliſhly?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou gav'ſt? thou, Lord, haſt tane away,</l>
                        <l>We bleſsings to thy Name ſhall pay.</l>
                        <l>Happy thy Church, my People, be,</l>
                        <l>At leaſt without, if not by Me.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:140"/>
                     <head>ODE XXVI. <hi>Vpon the Armies ſurprizall of the King at</hi> Holmeby, <hi>and the Enſuing diſtractions in the two Houſes, the Armie, and the City,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOord, Thou ſacred Unitie,</l>
                        <l>In an undivided Trine,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe combin'd in Mercy ſee;</l>
                        <l>Whom thy Iuſtice doth disjoyne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Save me from diſſenting Foes,</l>
                        <l>Who my Pray'rs and pity need;</l>
                        <l>And each other now oppoſe,</l>
                        <l>Though to fight with me agre'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>All diſcording parties guide,</l>
                        <l>To the Peace from which they ſway,</l>
                        <l>Whil'ſt they ſerve or Court a ſide,</l>
                        <l>Not the voice of Law obey.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Make me willingly to goe</l>
                        <l>Where thy Providence will lead:</l>
                        <l>And the change of things below,</l>
                        <l>In thy conſtant Preſence read.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Make me by thy skillfull Hand,</l>
                        <l>Such as thou would'ſt have me be;</l>
                        <l>Then waft me ſafely to that Land,</l>
                        <l>Where Peace ever dwells with thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:141"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Spare our Citie's (Lord) impure,</l>
                        <l>Through their Wealth and Plenty made;</l>
                        <l>In their multitude ſecure,</l>
                        <l>By Security betray'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Make them ſee, weigh, choſe and do</l>
                        <l>For thy Glory, and our Peace.</l>
                        <l>Leſt affliction like a Foe,</l>
                        <l>Arm'd for ſlaughter on them ſeize.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Enemies their ſins excite,</l>
                        <l>Long unfoyl'd they cannot be,</l>
                        <l>Who (their conſcience thwarting) fight</l>
                        <l>More againſt themſelves than Me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Guilt thy Iuſtice has purſu'd,</l>
                        <l>And for Rapin Wealth makes way:</l>
                        <l>Tumults grow from multitude;</l>
                        <l>Thoſe to confuſion betray.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though with mutuall forwardneſs,</l>
                        <l>They have ſet malicious Snares</l>
                        <l>Me in miſchief to oppreſs:</l>
                        <l>Be not yet my Ruine theirs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let me not ſo much debate,</l>
                        <l>What they do, or what I bear;</l>
                        <l>As my Saviour imitate,</l>
                        <l>And their Advocate appear.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:141"/>
                     <lg>
                        <l>That when longer Me to live,</l>
                        <l>Theſe extremities forbid;</l>
                        <l>Pray, Father them forgive!</l>
                        <l>For they knew not what they did.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Tears which to my Miſery,</l>
                        <l>They deny'd, to theirs deplore:</l>
                        <l>Which the leſs they ſpend for me,</l>
                        <l>For themſelves they need the more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My Blood light not on their Head,</l>
                        <l>Who my Crucifixion ſought:</l>
                        <l>By the fraud of ſome miſled,</l>
                        <l>Not by generall malice aught.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But thou, Lord, can'ſt with thy Care,</l>
                        <l>Me by ſuff'rings elevate;</l>
                        <l>Where thy Mercy's have more ſhare,</l>
                        <l>Than thy Iuſtice, or Mans hate.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="ode">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119890:142"/>
                     <head>ODE XXVII. <hi>Meditations upon Death after the votes of Non-Aadreſſes, and his Majeſty's cloſer Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in</hi> Carisbrook <hi>Caſtle.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THou that fill'ſt Heaven and Earth, O King of Kings,</l>
                        <l>In whom no Death, whence Life eternall Springs:</l>
                        <l>Who canſt our Souls unto the yawning Grave</l>
                        <l>Iuſtly condemne, or mercifully ſave.</l>
                        <l>Better be dead t'our ſelves, in thee ſurvive;</l>
                        <l>Than rob'd of Thee, and to our ſelves alive.</l>
                        <l>O let the bitter means that aggravate</l>
                        <l>My fall, thy Comforts in my Soul dilate.</l>
                        <l>If thou art with Me, fear ſhall not aſſail,</l>
                        <l>Though I ſhould walk along Deaths ſhady Vale.</l>
                        <l>Weak mortall man may with his Fate contend,</l>
                        <l>But 'tis thy Grace muſt ſtrength to vanquiſh lend.</l>
                        <l>Thou know'ſt as Man what 'tis to dy with Me,</l>
                        <l>Teach me by Death to live, my God, with Thee.</l>
                        <l>Though I ſhould dy I know thou ever liv'ſt:</l>
                        <l>Though thou ſhould'ſt kill, eternall Life thou giv'ſt.</l>
                        <l>O hold not back thy Love more wiſh'd than Breath,</l>
                        <l>O be not far, for neere perhaps is Death:</l>
                        <l>All the cloſe Snares for my Deſtruction ſet,</l>
                        <l>Thy Knowledg can diſcloſe, thy Power defeat.</l>
                        <l>Let me thy will diſcover that declares,</l>
                        <l>The good of Thine, through the much ill of theirs!</l>
                        <l>As I am Man I beg Thee turn away</l>
                        <l>This Cup; as Chriſtian I have learnt to Pray,</l>
                        <l>That not my will, but thine, my God, be done;</l>
                        <l>Mine into thine reſolve, and make them One.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:142"/>
                        <l>Let my deſires Life with leſs fervour woe,</l>
                        <l>Than thy Commands to ſuffer, or to doe.</l>
                        <l>As thou haſt pardon'd all my lives frail Errours,</l>
                        <l>So thou wilt ſave me from my Deaths falſe Terrours.</l>
                        <l>Make me content this nothing World to leave,</l>
                        <l>That all in thee (my All) I may receive.</l>
                        <l>My Foes their Duty to us both reject,</l>
                        <l>Let not thy mindfull Mercyes them neglect.</l>
                        <l>What profit by my blood can they obtain,</l>
                        <l>To looſe their Souls, though they my Kingdome gain.</l>
                        <l>Though my juſt Power againſt my ſelf they bent,</l>
                        <l>Let not themſelves have their juſt Puniſhment.</l>
                        <l>Thou by thy Son thy Mercy's haſt ally'd</l>
                        <l>To thoſe Offenders, by whom Crucify'd?</l>
                        <l>Whil'ſt violence he ſuff'red from his Foes,</l>
                        <l>Yet for their ſakes thoſe wrongs did freely chooſe.</l>
                        <l>O hear the Voice of his acquitting Blood,</l>
                        <l>Then the accuſing Cryes of mine more loud.</l>
                        <l>Let them their ſins, and thy full mercyes know,</l>
                        <l>Not their own Souls deceive and overthrow.</l>
                        <l>Tempted by unjuſt Power, extreams t'employ,</l>
                        <l>And by fallacious Juſtice me deſtroy.</l>
                        <l>Cruell as falſe their mercy's have I found,</l>
                        <l>Pretending to defend, they ſeek to wound.</l>
                        <l>Their bloody fraud O do not thou purſue;</l>
                        <l>But with thy Pity, and my Love ſubdue.</l>
                        <l>And for my Blood when Inquiſition</l>
                        <l>Thou mak'ſt; in that of thy beloved Son</l>
                        <l>Their Souls polluted, yet repentant dy;</l>
                        <l>That thy deſtroying Angel may paſs by.</l>
                        <l>They think my Realm's too narrow both to hold,</l>
                        <l>Let thy wide Mercy me, and them infold,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:119890:143"/>
                        <l>So by our Saviour reconcil'd to Thee,</l>
                        <l>Weel' live above ambitious Enmity.</l>
                        <l>When their hard, heavy Hands preſs down with harms,</l>
                        <l>O let me fall into thy tender Arms.</l>
                        <l>That from my Lifes ſad moments what away</l>
                        <l>Is cut, thy bleſt Eternity may pay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Lord thy divine Salvation clearly I</l>
                        <l>Have ſeen: in Peace O let thy Servant dy.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119890:143"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
